<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A non est inventus return'd to Mr. Edward Bagshaw's Enquiry, and vainly boasted discovery of weakness in the grounds of the churches infallibility also his seditious invectives against the moderate sincerity of Protestants, and savage cruelty against Roman Catholicks repressed / by a Catholick gentleman.</title>
            <author>Cressy, Serenus, 1605-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18518462</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18518462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">205240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1649:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A non est inventus return'd to Mr. Edward Bagshaw's Enquiry, and vainly boasted discovery of weakness in the grounds of the churches infallibility also his seditious invectives against the moderate sincerity of Protestants, and savage cruelty against Roman Catholicks repressed / by a Catholick gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Cressy, Serenus, 1605-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 115 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXII [1662]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cressy by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 24 misnumbered 42; p. 106-107 misnumbered 107-106.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671. --  Brief enquiry into the grounds and reasons, whereupon the infallibility of the Pope and Church of Rome is said to be founded.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Infallibility.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A <hi>NON EST INVENT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Return'd to Mr. EDWARD BAGSHAW'S ENQUIRY, AND Vainly boaſted DISCOVERY Of weakneſs in the Grounds of the CHURCHES INFALLIBILITY.</p>
            <p>ALSO His Seditious INVECTIVES Againſt the Moderate Sincerity of PROTESTANTS, and ſavage Cruelty againſt ROMAN CATHOLICKS <hi>Repreſſed</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Catholick Gentleman.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALM. LXIII. <hi>v.</hi> VI.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scrutati ſunt Iniquitates; defecerunt Scrutinio.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>They made an Enquiry after Iniquities; but the Enquirers failed in the Enquiry.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, MDCLXII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205240:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205240:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>Edward Bagſhaw,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Title of your Book is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt, being called only <hi>An Enquiry into the Grounds of the Roman Churches Infallibility;</hi> But by pronouncing in the concluſion thoſe fatall words, <hi>MENE TEKEL,</hi> you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently declare, it cannot be anſwered: The deſtruction of the <hi>Babilonian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> was not more inevitable after the writing that <hi>Decretory</hi> ſentence by an inviſible Angels fingers, than is the <hi>Roman Churches</hi> now. You have compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and publiſhed this your Book, which you judge unanſwerable, and (to deal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly with you) ſo may I too, though I be as good a <hi>Catholick</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. What would you have more? A reaſon for it? Have but a little patience and you ſhall not fail of one, better then you expect, or have knowledge to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet I conceive it concerns not <hi>Catholicks</hi> only, but the whole Kingdom,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205240:3"/> I mean <hi>all good Subjects</hi> in it, that ſuch a book, though pretendedly againſt Roman Catholicks only, yet full of pernicious invectives, malicious complaints, and ſeditious reflexions againſt the State, ſhould with a barefac'd impudence ſtalke abroad in the publick view, as fearleſs of a cenſure. Nor is the Book in it ſelf ſo highly provoking, as in reſpect of the abominable Preface that no honeſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, Proteſtant or Catholick, can read without indignation, no reader juſtify or not miſlike without declaring his Thirſt after the publick ruine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles advice of <hi>redeeming the time</hi> forbids me to miſpend it by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying line after line to what you have written: That therefore which <hi>I</hi> have to ſay to you ſhall be to make good theſe poſitions in direct oppoſition to what you have written, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. That it is againſt the welfare of Engliſh ſubjects, both for body and ſoul, that you, and ſuch as you ſhould be permitted to call your ſelves Proteſtants, and members of the Engliſh Church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. That your inſtilling ſuſpicions into the peoples minds, as if Engliſh Divines, &amp;c. had a deſign to introduce Popery again, is a meer acting over the late Rebellion.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205240:3"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. That your attempt to render Roman Catholick ſubjects only in an incapacity of Toleration, is more groundleſſe, and in your mouthes moſt maliciouſly ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. That your whole diſcourſe againſt the <hi>Churches Infallibility</hi> only proves that you have nothing to ſay to the purpoſe againſt it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That it is a publick miſchief that Mr.</hi> Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, <hi>or any ſuch as he, ſhould be permitted to call themſelves Engliſh Proteſtants.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IF common fame be true, Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> you are the ſame perſon that publiſhed ſo petulant and uncivil a Libel againſt my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> and not for that fault alone have been ſo deſervedly Diſciplined by Mr. <hi>l'Eſtrange,</hi> and ſo ſmartly whip't, that the whole Town has heard your cries. How then comes it to paſs that you can find leaſure to ſeek out, and defy to the combat other enemies? But it may be the demoliſhing of the Roman Church
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205240:4"/> is but an excurſion in a <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> whilſt you are, for your divertiſement, unbending your thoughts, or taking breath awhile againſt a new combat, with an Adverſary that has a great deal more zeal, ſharpneſs, honeſty and courage then is for your purpoſe, who hope not to be diſcern'd, whilſt in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of <hi>the Act of Oblivion</hi> you will not ſuffer either the <hi>King</hi> or any of his faithfull <hi>Subjects</hi> to forget what they have ſuffered, and muſt expect, but ſtill work and preach and print, almoſt <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidem Verbis</hi> as you did when the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Covenant was the only Religion and Goſpel of the three Kingdoms.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe practices, Mr. L<hi>'Estrange,</hi> if he cannot interrupt, yet he can call company, and bid them take notice of them. He will not permit you to Glory as if you could once more couzen the Kingdom into a <hi>new Rebellion.</hi> Never hope to find ſo much as one <hi>Engliſh Protestant</hi> that will once more be cheated to look upon you as the <hi>Aſſertors of the Subjects Liberties,</hi> or maintainers of pure <hi>Protestant Religion.</hi> If the <hi>Civil Authority</hi> will for ever wink at your <hi>Caballs,</hi> and the <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> leave open the <hi>Pulpits</hi> to your Sermons of the old
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205240:4"/> ſtile, and the <hi>Preſſes</hi> to your Pamphlets againſt <hi>Biſhops</hi> and indifferent <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies:</hi> If you expect <hi>Indemnity</hi> muſt be interpreted to regard the future alſo, all that can be ſaid will be, <hi>Sani, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brii, vigiles perîmus.</hi> We ſhall not, as heretofore, be ſurpriſed: but we <hi>make a Covenant with destruction,</hi> as if we were afraid it would eſcape us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for your <hi>Pamphlet</hi> touching <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> though by the Title you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to attacque only <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and to demoliſh the <hi>Grounds of the Churches Faith,</hi> yet in the whole <hi>Book</hi> there are not quite two ſmall leaves wherein the <hi>Church</hi> is concern'd at all either in its Grounds or Superſtructure. Therefore I am confident, and it may be <hi>Mr. L'Eſtrange</hi> (who knows your wayes and Arts much better then I) may in a far neater, that is, his own ſtile tell you, your real Deſign was to write a Book with the <hi>Title</hi> againſt <hi>Catholicks,</hi> meerly to have an opportunity to ſtuffe the <hi>Preface</hi> with malicious glances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Proteſtants too, and incenſe vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar minds, as if <hi>Popery</hi> (forſooth) were ready to be introduced.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Now though my ſelf, purely as a <hi>Catholick,</hi> am little concern'd in that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205240:5"/> part of your book which you purpoſely wrote againſt <hi>Catholicks;</hi> and not very much in thoſe paſſages againſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> except only in this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you would fain make <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion</hi> your <hi>Engine</hi> to raiſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, yet as a faithfull <hi>Subject</hi> to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and a lover of my Countries peace, I cannot but inwardly bewail, and muſt take leave thus publickly to juſtifie the too reaſonable cauſe of my grief, when I ſee an Engliſh Subject o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly profeſſing his name, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Protection of an <hi>Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Counſellour of State,</hi> renew the old ſeditious practiſe of inflaming the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples minds with rage againſt their <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> and murmuring ſuſpicions againſt their <hi>Governours:</hi> A practiſe that above all others contributed to the raiſing of the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and to the ruine and murder of our <hi>late Soveraign of happy memory,</hi> and his beſt Subjects and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> &amp;c. Here are ſtill among us God knowes how many <hi>Sects,</hi> that if any <hi>Proteſtant Doctours</hi> ſhall preſume to ſpeak or write other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then according to what the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous zeal of <hi>Sectaries</hi> againſt Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205240:5"/> Unity and peace ſuggeſts, they muſt preſently be expoſed to a general ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion, the Country muſt be raiſed upon them, and upon the Biſhops if they not <hi>diſcountenance</hi> them, and upon the <hi>King</hi> unleſs he puniſh them for no fault at all.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But give me leave now, Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> to ask. <hi>Who are you? of what Sect? Of what Church?</hi> Common report gives you for a Presbyterian, a man former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very buſie in the <hi>Intrigues</hi> of that <hi>Faction.</hi> Yet ſome paſſages in your <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory</hi> ſpeak you an <hi>Independent:</hi> in which you call your ſelf <hi>an Aſſertor of Christian Liberty,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the <hi>keenneſs of Laws againſt ſuch;</hi> a diſliker of <hi>Epiſcopal Authority as ſetled in</hi> England; and one that <hi>refuſes to admit the interpretation of Scripture from any Perſon or Church, but only from your own private Reaſon.</hi> Moſt likely it is, you reſerve <hi>in petto</hi> a Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether party you mean to adhere to, till you ſee how they are likely to thrive: till then you would paſs for an <hi>Amphibion.</hi> And truly ſuch a temper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you threatens much danger to the State. When <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> are made friends, Chriſt muſt look to himſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If you be an <hi>Independent</hi> on all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205240:6"/> will you not ſuffer others to be Independent likewiſe on you? Or if you be a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> are you not content with enjoying hitherto the fruits of his <hi>Majesties</hi> moſt gracious promiſe from <hi>Breda?</hi> None pretend more then you to tender conſciences. Have any <hi>call'd</hi> you in <hi>question for differences in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> But this it ſeems will not ſerve your turn: Nor an <hi>Independents</hi> turn. Your <hi>tender conſcience</hi> will not accept of the only condition that his <hi>Majesty</hi> annexes to this his <hi>Grace,</hi> which is, That you <hi>must not diſturb the peace of the Kingdom.</hi> This moſt <hi>just</hi> and <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary condition</hi> you here in your Preface renounce, in which you again blow the Trumpet to ſedition, by telling the World that Engliſh Divines are bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Popery. If that were true, as long as it may be permitted to you to be <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Independents</hi> among your ſelves, what do you complain of? Will you never leave this peeviſh, this malicious envy, not to content your ſelves with your own ſafety unleſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be ruin'd?</p>
               <p n="6">6. But it is intolerable that you ſhould call your ſelves in your Preface, <hi>We Protestants:</hi> and talke of <hi>our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:205240:6"/> 
                  <hi>Church of England,</hi> or <hi>our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors, Our primitive proteſtancy,</hi> &amp;c. Are you an Engliſh Proteſtant? a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Engliſh Church eſtabliſhed by Law and Canons? Why then do you not ſubmit peaceably to the government of your Biſhops, and indifferent Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies? Why do you reject the Book of Common Prayer enacted by ſupreme authority both Spiritual and Temporal to be the publick Liturgy of the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>England?</hi> Why do you find fault with the keenneſs of Laws againſt ſuch Aſſertors of Chriſtian Liberty? The very titles you aſſume of Presbyterian or Independent, declare that your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal eſſence conſiſts in an oppoſition to Engliſh proteſtancy and prelacy. You pilfer therefore the name of an Engliſh Proteſtant, <hi>ut ſportulam furunculus,</hi> to uſe <hi>Tertullians</hi> phraſe: Or rather you are Engliſh proteſtants, as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſays ſome in his time were Chriſtians, <hi>in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probium &amp; contumeliam Chriſti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. But you are wiſe in your genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: you know you could do no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, unleſs you took a vizard. For if you had ſpoken in your Preface the true Language of a Sectary; if directing your ſpeech to <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> you had ſaid,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205240:7"/> 
                  <hi>I</hi> Mr. Edward Bagſhaw, <hi>Student of</hi> Chriſt-Church, <hi>a very Presbyterian (or Independent) a profeſſed Rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Engliſh Church, do out of my tender love and care of the welfare and promotion of the ſaid Church, give you, O Engliſh Proteſtants, warning to take heed of Popery, for the bringing in of which among you Doctour</hi> Gunning <hi>and</hi> Mr. Thorndike, <hi>and God knowes how many more are preparing way; the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are of intelligence with them, and the State connives at them: Therefore look to your ſelves. All we can do is to blow the Trumpet, and tell you once more how couragiouſly we will lead you to a thorough Reformation: If you have neither zeal for God, nor knowledge of your own ſtrength, 'tis none of our fault, Little do you know that we Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Anabaptiſts Quakers, &amp;e. are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain become good friends, and will joyne together to put down this Antichriſtian Hierarchy; and when we are to divide their lands it will be time to try which of us can get most. Now a beater Meane</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:205240:7"/> 
                  <hi>we have not for ſuch a purpoſe then, as formerly we did, to cry out, Beware of Popery, Take heed of your Antichriſtian Clergy, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. If you had unwiſely diſcovered your thoughts with ſuch plainneſſe, your open dealing would have ſhewed ſome ſincerity, ſome appearance of the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the <hi>Dove,</hi> but little of the ſubtle wiſdom of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> a quality much more for your purpoſe. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, your vizard being quite worne out, your calling your ſelves Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants will not have the effect it had in your former happy dayes twenty years ſince. Your Voice is too well known now not to be <hi>Jacobs,</hi> There is ſcarce an Engliſh ſubject ſo ignorant, or of ſo ſhort a memory, but can take notice that this was the <hi>Old Tune that ſounded to a charge,</hi> and invited them to kill one another for Charities ſake, and to ſuffer you know whom, to murther the beſt King that ever reigned before him. The difference between the two Brethren in iniquity, being only this; One did but fight againſt him, and the Other killed him; One bound his hand, and the other cut off his head: They will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205240:8"/> be ſo far from ſtartling at the name of Popery out of your mouthes, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they may begin to entertain a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion of a Religion ſo perſecuted by you, eſpecially remembring that the Papiſts never ſeparated their intereſts from the Kings and Theirs, but unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ventured their lives and eſtates for them, and this purely out of love, Duty and conſcience, even when all they could expect by a victory was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtill under the penalty of the Laws.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Therefore a diſguiſe is neceſſary for you whenſoever you would ſpeak, except to your own Party in private. It had been folly in extremity to ſay, <hi>We Presbyterians, Independents, &amp;c. do give you Engliſh Proteſtants warning to beware of your Doctours that would bring in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> It had been apparently to your own prejudice, unleſs you had ſaid, <hi>We tell you this who are true Reformed Engliſh Protestants, of the ſame Church with you, your Paſtours, who have care of your ſouls, whom you ſee no man hinders from preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your Pulpits, and writing Books to Preach to thoſe that cannot hear us in Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits. If we were enemies would the Civill or Eccleſiaſtical State, think you, allow us ſuch a liberty, and maintain us at their charges to Preach and Print as we do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:205240:8"/> 10. But I do aſſure you Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> you are no Engliſh Proteſtant, For <hi>what is it to be an Engliſh Proteſtant,</hi> or <hi>a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Engliſh Church?</hi> This is a queſtion of greater moment then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily is believed: The very ſubſiſtence of Proteſtant Religion in <hi>England</hi> now depends upon the right ſtating of it. Nay I may truly ſay, that even we Roman Catholicks are much concerned in it, and therefore I may be pardoned if I inſiſt upon it; becauſe unleſs this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be reſolved, all our diſputes with Proteſtants are likely to prove meer beating of the air, contentions utterly wandring from the purpoſe. Therefore I may be excuſed, if I take the trouble upon me to reſolve it: and this I muſt do, not upon <hi>Catholick</hi> grounds, or notions of the phraſe <hi>[being members of a Church]</hi> but only the notions which Proteſtants and generally all Sects divided from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks have entertained of that phraſe. For Catholicks do not eſteem any one a member of the Roman Catholick Church, that doth not profeſs all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines without exception taught by it to be true, and ſubmits not to all the Lawes and Ordinances of it. There is no diſtinction to be made, as to this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205240:9"/> matter, between Doctrines in themſelves Fundamental or non-Fundamental, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Lawes in themſelves neceſſary or not: becauſe a refuſal to accept any one of thoſe Lawes or Doctrines does vertually deſtroy the Authority of the Church, of how little concernment ſo ever ſuch a Doctrine or Ordinance be in it ſelf. There may be differences and even diſſentions among Catholicks, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout points of far greater moment in themſelves, and yet neither of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be in danger of being excluded from the Title of Catholiks, or members of the Roman Catholick Church, becauſe the Churches Authority has not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it ſelf in thoſe diſputes either way, and therefore is untouched by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But generally all Congregations divided from the Catholick have a quite different conceit of the Phraſe <hi>[being Members of a Church:]</hi> And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is either general, or more ſpecial. According to the general conception of that phraſe they acknowledge all to be members of their Church (or rather co-members of the Church of Chriſt) that do not teach doctrines or make or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances excluding all right and intereſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205240:9"/> in the common ſalvation: and thus En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh proteſtants eſteem themſelves mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Catholick Church, and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> Church, and you Presbyterians, Independents, &amp;c. of the Engliſh proteſtant Church: becauſe they do not deny a poſſibility of ſalvation to one another notwithſtanding the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences among them.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The ſecond and more ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the phraſe <hi>[being Members of a Church]</hi> entertained by all particular Congregations not Catholick, does im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port an external conformity in all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines without exception, and all pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes determined by each congregation reſpectively, a renunciation of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the refuſers from an external communion and participation of the priviledges of that Congregation, who notwithſtanding may be acknowledged to be almoſt in as good a condition as to ſalvation, as thoſe are which exclude them from their external Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Thus <hi>Lutherans</hi> are not <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> though they believe <hi>Calviniſts</hi> may meet them in heaven, becauſe they will not admit them to their communion. Thus you Presbyterians and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, &amp;c. are no Engliſh proteſtants as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205240:10"/> long as you are Non-Conformiſts. Let the differences between you be never ſo ſmall [as wearing a Surplice, Kneeling at Communion, &amp;c.] if theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies be eſtabliſhed by Lawes Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, the non-ſubmiſſion to them is a manifeſt dividing from that Church: and the leſs conſiderable the quarrels are, the greater is the guilt of thoſe that publickly diſpute or write againſt that Church of which they deſire to be thought members. True it is you would ſeem to have ſome reaſon to complain againſt the Engliſh Church, if for ſuch trifling differencies only, they ſhould pronounce you excommunicated from Chriſts Myſtical Body: (though they muſt give me leave to ſay, That by not doing ſo, but acknowledging your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations to be members of the Church, they do manifeſtly conclude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of Schiſme by ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with you, whom they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny to be Schiſmaticks:) But it would be ridiculous in you to accuſe them of Tyranny for excluding you from their External Communion, when you your ſelves will not embrace it. They do not pretend to an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to oblige you in conſcience to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205240:10"/> believe that their Doctrines are true and their Ordinances juſt: but they would be no Church, they would renounce all Order, if they did not maintain the laws and cuſtomes with ſo great deliberation, and after ſo many diſputes with you, framed and renewed. Where there is no Uniformity even in external matters, there is no Church, but a <hi>Babel.</hi> If at Communion ſome ſhould ſit, others ſtand, others lye along, (as our Lord did) and others kneel, if ſome ſhould be bare-headed, others with their hats on, would it looke like an aſſembly of men that ſerved God? Therefore complain not, but rather thank God and them, if they force not your conſciences, but permit you to abſtain from things you do not like, and to practice among your ſelves things you like better. But to expect to be acknowledged members of a Church, whilſt you refuſe to ſubmit to the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of that Church in things of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not evil, much more whilſt you write publickly againſt them, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them not to pretend to the name of a Church. Therefore, I conclude, that <hi>you Mr.</hi> Bagſhaw <hi>are no more a member of the Engliſh Church, then I am:</hi> and my proofe is this very <hi>Preface</hi> of your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205240:11"/> Book that I now write againſt. Your ſaying that Epiſcopacy is lawful, or your being ordained by Biſhops, ſignifies nothing; as long as you diſobey them, you are none of their ſubjects.</p>
               <p n="13">13. However I cannot blame you, if in deſpight of Engliſh proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves you will needs be called <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh proteſtants.</hi> For if being, as really you are, no true members of the Engliſh Church, you were treated as ſuch, that is, excluded from a participation of the emoluments of it, and obliged to a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated exerciſe of your ill-natur'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, two great incommodities would enſue to you, and withal two as propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably great benefits to them, and the whole Nation.</p>
               <p n="14">14. For <hi>First,</hi> What pittiful Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations would you in a ſhort time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be? At preſent your numbers, eſpecially in Cities and Towns are not unconſiderable. Whereas, if being no members of the Engliſh Church, you were excluded from participating Tithes, Benefices and other preferments, not at all due to you, and had no other main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance but the Voluntary contributions of your own party, you would quickly find that Party weary of you, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205240:11"/> become rather content to hear a ſermon in the Church, and wholeſome prayers in a Surplice, then to pay ſo much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus for far worſe ſtuffe in a parlour, from a ſhort cloak and no caſſack.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The <hi>Second Mortification</hi> thence flowing would be yet more intolerable. Hitherto the facility of Biſhops giving you leave to call your ſelves Engliſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and members of their Church enables you to defile their Churches by doing your own buſineſſe in them to their great prejudice and danger. In their pulpits you cry down Ceremonies, you preach againſt their government, you ſow ſedition in the hearts of their flock, you inſtill diſcontent againſt the State: In a word you do all the miſchief you can, both to it and them. And all this while you enjoy their Livings: they maintain you to deſtroy them. Whereas if at the charges of your own patrons only you were to preach and pray in private parlours, your peculiar Gifts in both would quickly vaniſh: for there would be no uſe of rayling, and blowing up diſcontented paſſions in an Auditory, where moſt of your hearers can raile as well as your ſelves, and are perhaps al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready more diſcontented: You would loſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205240:12"/> the pleaſure of gaining <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to your Faction; becauſe none will hear you that are in danger of being ſeduced. On the contrary to your hearts torment you would ſee even City-Churches eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day more and more filled with your deareſt friends; nay your own Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks would come down, and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, yea even bread, you would quickly digeſt both Croſſe and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Before I leave this Argument, I would fain with your permiſſion propoſe a Queſtion to You, though I fear the very propoſal will anger You, and I do ſcarce hope for an Anſwer, though if you had a mind to it, nothing is more eaſie to be anſwered: and in caſe you reply to this paper, remember, I ſummon You not to forget this queſtion.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Suppoſe then <hi>His Majesty</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould by Law confirme to You the gratious promiſe from <hi>Breda,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That upon giving ſecurity not to enter into practiſes to diſturbe the publick peace, You ſhould not be called in queſtion for matters of opinion, but ſhould have a moderate liberty to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe your Religion at home </q> (or even in Churches to your own party only,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205240:12"/> with prohibition to all good ſubjects to come to your ſermons) <q rend="margQuotes"> would you be content with ſuch an indulgence and mercie from the State? Would You upon theſe termes engage to diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your ſermons and prayers top-ful of the <hi>fel draconum?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. Till You anſwer this Queſtion, I will tell You the Opinion of many that believe they know Your temper well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. They do aſſure themſelves you would not: You, I mean, Presbyterians and Independents: For as for your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural brood, and ſubdivided Sects of Anabaptiſts, Quakers, &amp;c. I conceive they are more reaſonable in this matter of Liberty of conſcience. They would be content to ſerve God after their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion in their own Chambers, and would maintain their own Miniſters, and poor too, paying withall the dues which by Law belong to Pariſhes. Whereas there is but too good ground to believe that there is nothing more apprehended by You Presbyterians and Independents, then ſuch an Indulgence: becauſe that would diſunite from you all other Sects, and make them ſure to the State againſt You: ſo that You and your Friends would ſtand miſerably and contemptibly alone.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:205240:13"/> 19. True it is, you would fain ſeem ſomwhat inclined to a <hi>Conformity</hi> of your faſhion, and for that end You demand Conferences and Treaties with the Biſhops, &amp;c. But withall You require a condeſcendence from them in ſuch things, as both honour and truth forbid a compliance in, and which cannot be granted without a ſecret acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they have been faulty hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in oppreſſing You with undue burdens. And as for other trifling ſcruples of yours, You are more troubled when they yield any thing, then when they refuſe all. However by ſuch Treaties You gain this, that among Vulgar minds You may ſometimes paſs for zealous perſons in all things pertaining to God, and withall no enemies to peace: And beſides; You may have occaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to complain yet more againſt Biſhops, for not ſubmitting to your conditions, ſo eaſie and reaſonable. For alas! You deſire eaſe only in indifferent trifling matters: whereas in all neceſſary Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances for Gods glory You are ready to comply. What a great matter, ſay You, is a Surplice, or refuſing a Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ical Croſs? For peace ſake You will even digeſt Epiſcopacy. Let there be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205240:13"/> Biſhops, but not <hi>jure Divino,</hi> or if <hi>jure Divino,</hi> not ſuch as Law hath eſtabliſhed. Let them be countermanded each Biſhop by a dozen Presbyters, and ſubject to their Claſſes, and you will not ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Title.</p>
               <p n="20">20. I dare ſay, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> You are very angrie now to be told thus publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>that you are more afraid of Liberty of Conſcience then of perſecution,</hi> unleſs You might have leave to interpret <hi>Liberty of conſcience,</hi> to be a free permiſſion to do miſchief, not to ſerve God. And much more, to be told, You are no Engliſh proteſtant. But You muſt pardon us, that cannot but think ſo, till You tell the World what You mean by an Engliſh proteſtant, and what that Engliſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy is which You profeſſe and maintaine, and have been ſo buſie Twenty Years, almoſt to the ruine of the Kingdome, to ſet up againſt <hi>Prelacy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:205240:14"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That</hi> Mr. Bagſhaw<hi>'s inſttilling ſupicions into the Peoples minds, as if Engliſh Divines, &amp;c. had a deſigne to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Popery again, is a mere acting over the late Rebellion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IT is now time to take into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the zeal, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> that You, as a good Engliſh Proteſtant, have ſhew'd againſt thoſe that have a liking to the <hi>pompe of popery,</hi> and are ſo hardy as to make ſome attempts to bring it back into your Church. In this zeal You ſpare neither <hi>Gentry</hi> (including I ſuppoſe the <hi>Nobility)</hi> nor <hi>Clergy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Firſt as touching the <hi>Gentry,</hi> You tell the Kingdom that <hi>too many of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
                  <hi>Gentry begin already to be taken with the outward pompe of popery.</hi> Who are theſe many, <hi>too many?</hi> They are Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen. The Gentry indeed are not ſo apt to be wrought upon by You, as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour <hi>Tradesmen</hi> and <hi>day-laborours:</hi> and therfore it is much for your purpoſe, that the general rout ſhould have a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205240:14"/> of them. Well though there be <hi>many</hi> of them, yet You name none: whereas there are but two of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and You name them both. There is ſome <hi>Mystery</hi> in this. Would You not have it believed, but dare not ſpeak out, that theſe <hi>too many Gentlemen</hi> are ſome members of the preſent Parliament, that you covertly deſire the Kingdome may ſuſpect, and have an ill opinion of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not, in compliance with your ſlovenly devotion, ſuffer you to burne Surplices and Copes, or abrogate decent Ceremonies? but much more becauſe ſeveral Honourable perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them have expreſſed ſome pity to Roman Catholicks, and an inclination to requite their fidelity with ſome ſmall eaſe from the heavy burdens laid on them by the Lawes? It is a greater torment to You to ſee their Fidelity rewarded, then their Religion not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. But it is intolerable to you, that no good Chriſtian now can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied in the way that Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks have taken to appear fit objects of mercy, ſince they have both publickly in the houſe of Lords <hi>Vivâ voce,</hi> and by many Treatiſes and Proteſtations in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting given ſuch ſecurity of their unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205240:15"/> 
                  <hi>Loyalty</hi> and Obedience to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and the State, as not any Chriſtian can poſſibly give greater, and I much fear You will never have the honeſty to imitate them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Obſerve one thing I pray You, in ſuch Proteſtations and writings of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks. They do not deprecate any former faults committed, becauſe they are guiltie of none: they proteſt their clearneſs from thoſe crimes of <hi>a few deſperate unhappy monſters,</hi> and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of their traiterous Maſters, that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the ſeverity of Laws againſt all: They do not mention their univerſal fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie to the King theſe laſt twentie Years, as an obligation or merit, for which they expect reward from men: but as a <hi>neceſſary duty</hi> to which their Religion bound them, and which if they had not performed, they ſhould have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred a curſe from God. Yet all this perhaps will not ſatisfie You. But ſee our different Complexion: for my part though there were not one of Your (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) Religion, but were deeply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in infidelity to the King, yet if You would only acknowledg that a fault was committed, is repented of, and a promiſe made of Loyalty for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205240:15"/> I ſhould hope well, and wiſh You might be believed and confided in for the future.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Next as to the <hi>Clergy,</hi> Your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation <note place="margin">Preface.</note> is moſt heavy and punctual when You ſay, <q rend="margQuotes"> I need not plead for the not perſecuting of Poperie, &amp;c. when ſome that yet profeſſe themſelves to be of our Church, and thoſe of good note too, are not afraid to plead for ſomthing more then its Toleration. Since by telling us in print, that the Pope is not <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Maſter</hi> Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike <hi>in Weights and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</hi>
                     </note> Antichriſt, That Papiſts are not Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; nay by affirming, That all are ſchiſmaticks who upon that ſcore do refuſe communion with them, they not only blemiſh the vertue and piety of our firſt Reformers, who all built upon that foundation, but likewiſe ſhew how willing they are upon any termes how wretched and unworthie ſoever, to returne into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and bring us to our Brick and bondage again. If this be not the intereſt of ſome, I cannot imagine what means the crying up of that Great <hi>Diana</hi> of the Papiſts, the <hi>Churches Authority,</hi> and making that the ſole Interpreter of Scripture, The <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>upon</hi> Math. 9.</note> preaching up of <hi>Lent,</hi> and other poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Fiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>daies, as Religious Faſts, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205240:16"/> of Apoſtolical Inſtitution, quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <note place="margin">
                        <hi>M. Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike</hi> ut ſuprà.</note> both to expreſs ſcripture, and an Act of Parliament. The inſinuating, that we may lawfully pray for the dead, and likewiſe expect ſome benefit by their prayers, which in time may eaſily be improved to our praying unto them. Theſe with ſome other opinions of the like nature, ſo far degenerating from our primitive proteſtancy, do ſhew that if the Age is willing to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, there are not wanting learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men who are willing enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. This <hi>authority</hi> that You, Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> take upon You to proſcribe all proteſtants that dare not profeſs ſuch a deteſtation of <hi>Catholick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> as Your <hi>party</hi> does, is alone ſufficient to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate how much the <hi>Engliſh Clergy</hi> does neglect their own preſervation, whilſt they permit ſuch as You to call your ſelves proteſtants, and <hi>members of their Church:</hi> your waies and intereſts being ſo directry oppoſed to theirs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>All England</hi> almoſt has lately heard <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</note> laid to the charge of the late moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly murdered Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> as the moſt heavy point of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, <hi>that he had a deſire of restoring</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:205240:16"/> 
                  <hi>England to Catholick unity.</hi> Yet there was not produced any proof at all, that for that end he deſerted any neceſſarie and eſſential Doctrines of his own Church: the mere deſire of <hi>unity</hi> was his crime. A crime that he willingly acknowledged, and as he had reaſon joyfullie boaſted of. And certainly, that Chriſtian muſt needs be full of a <hi>Spirit not from heaven,</hi> that hates unitie, <hi>quatenus ipſam.</hi> Now, what my Lord Archbiſhop deſired, and died for, I am perſwaded there is ſcarce any <hi>true ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Engliſh proteſtant</hi> but does com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend in him, and would not refuſe, occaſion being given, to imitate him in.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If you read Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> his works both Engliſh and Latine, You <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews</note> will, even in his <hi>Controverſies</hi> againſt Catholicks, find a wonderful caution not to aggravate, or multiply differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, great care to prevent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and an exactneſs in ſtating diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted points with a moſt ſtudied impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, &amp; very oft with condeſcendence. Nay even in his ſermons before the Court, in which his heart only ſpoke as as an Embaſſadour for God, what pangs may one perceive in his ſoul when he speaks
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205240:17"/> upon this ſubject, and reflects on the averſion that ſome who like You, call themſelves proteſtants, have from Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick peace and Unitie. Hearken to this one paſſage in his firſt Sermon on <hi>Pentecoſt: Who ſhall make us of one accord? High ſhall his reward be in heaven, and happy his remembrance on earth, that ſhall be the means to restore this accord to the Church; that once we may keep a true and perfect Pentecost, like this here,</hi> Erant om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes unanimiter. It was a reſtoring of unity that he ſo much thirſted after: which word ſhewes, that he had a reſpect to the Catholick Church from which only a ſeparation was made.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And Doctour <hi>Steward</hi> likewiſe, a perſon as repleniſhed with learning, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doctour</hi> Steward.</note> and vertue as any of his time, he ſo longed after this unitie, that in his laſt Will he gave order it ſhould be the argument of the Inſcription on his Tombe. And no doubt there is, but ſuch an Inſcription would make it lighter, that is, render his future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition better.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Theſe wothy perſons were indeed Engliſh proteſtants, like thoſe You now arraign. They knew the true compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of their own Chuch: A Church,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205240:17"/> though I muſt needs ſay, not firmly built yet however erected by advice of perſons in <hi>Authority,</hi> perſons of honour and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: not as <hi>Geneva, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Cromwels Independent Church,</hi> by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Army of Tradesmen. They knew that at the firſt framing of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Church a way was not ſo wholly given to paſſion, but that when certain intereſts of a few great perſons were complied with, and ſeveral too juſtly complained of <hi>Gravamina</hi> from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Court remedied, there might be a poſſibility of cloſing again with that Church which they then only ſo far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted. They knew there was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intention ſo to forſake the Roman Church, as if it were a <hi>Babel,</hi> or <hi>ſeat of Antichriſt,</hi> but ever acknowledged it a true Church, though not ſo well <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi> On the contrarie <hi>they knew,</hi> and their <hi>ſucceſſors</hi> do ſtill to your hearts torment acknowledg, that all the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Juriſdiction</hi> of the Engliſh Church is derived from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: which therefore muſt be a true <hi>Church</hi> if theirs be any.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Upon ſuch grounds as theſe, no queſtion, my Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> not only deſired, as all honeſt well
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205240:18"/> minded Proteſtants do, but alſo hoped, that if by his <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>skill</hi> he could reduce the Engliſh church to that primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive State before your <hi>Calviniſtical</hi> dregs and poiſon were inſtilled into it, he might, upon warrantable terms, procure a <hi>Re-union</hi> with the Catholick Church. But how ſhould this Re-union be made? By giving up to Roman Catholicks all the points of Engliſh Doctrins and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline? No ſuch matter. But this he knew, That in Books of Controverſy, among <hi>ten Points</hi> diſputed, there are not two wherein either of the Churches are intereſted: and that moſt of the few, real, Subſtantial differences might be qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a moderate interpretation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendence.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But whenſoever ſuch a buſineſs as this is either agitated or talked of, you Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> and your <hi>party</hi> ſmile, and deride us poor Roman Catholicks, as if we vainly framed to our ſelves great hopes and advantages by ſuch good Chriſtian deſignes, or Writings of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. But truly you are deceived. We indeed, as we ought, are glad, purely for their ſakes that either deſigne or write ſincerely and ingenuouſly in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion. But ſuch deſigns and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205240:18"/> Writings are harmeful to us in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition: and the reaſon is plain: becauſe they being the works of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons without any publick com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; of perſons that have no ſufficient influence upon the whole Engliſh Church and State, they produce little effect: On the contrary they give only an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſuch malicious tongues and pens as Yours to Alarme the whole Kingdome both againſt them and us.</p>
               <p n="12">12. But if it would pleaſe his ſacred Majeſtie or the Parliament to allow a modeſt Conference (not Diſpute) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a certain number of ſober learned Engliſh Proteſtants and Catholicks, by means of which a clear view might be given what the peculiar Doctrines by <hi>Authority</hi> eſtabliſhed on both ſides are, and what place may be allowed for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Interpretations and Condeſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in all probability the ſucceſs could not but be moſt happy: the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea all Chriſtendom would ſtand in a maze to ſee what an ineſtimable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing has been ſo long wanting to <hi>England,</hi> and how little cauſe there was it ſhould be refuſed. How would the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical State of theſe nations be eſtabliſhed and united in intereſts with all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205240:19"/> the Chriſtian world almoſt? How free ſhould we all be from the leaſt danger of being infected with the venom of Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and how ſecure from their deſignes? For then they would to all eyes appear in their diſtinct bodies: it would be ſeen who, how many, and how qualified they are: and permiſſion being allowed them for a private liberty of exerciſing their Religions reſpectively, any ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding tumults would be both eaſily repreſſed, and their cauſe appear inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable. In a word Religion as it might by common Advice be ſetled in this Kingdom, would deſerve to be the envy and pattern to all the world beſides, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eaſily freed from many abuſes much complained of, but hard to be rectified in other Catholick Countries.</p>
               <p n="13">13. And whence comes the obſtruction to ſo inconceivable and univerſal a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as this, but meerly from ſuch, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Proteſtants as You and Your partie are permitted to call your ſelves. From You it proceeds that the Eccleſiaſticks of this Kingdom have not hitherto ſo much as endeavoured to convert us Roman Catholicks to their Religion: They have been unwilling to be informed what the true Differences between us
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205240:19"/> and themſelves are. As if true Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion did formally conſiſt in a blind, heady, and voluntary breach of Unity with all Churches before them. They have condeſcended to admit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences with Sects, whoſe peculiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion conſiſting in an incompoſſibility with their government renders them irreconcileable, unleſs they yield up both their Faith and Eſtates. Yea for ſuch Enemies ſatisfaction (if any thing could ſatisfie them) they have ſubmitted to alterations even in their Church office and Diſcipline. Laſtly to content ſuch Engliſh Proteſtants as You, they have connived at your defiling, altering and deſtroying that which heretofore was called, and by Law ſtill is truly the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant Religion:</hi> As will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear even by what You are ſuffered here to write againſt eminent perſons of their Church.</p>
               <p n="14">14. You proſcribe and expoſe to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick hatred Doctour <hi>Gunning</hi> and Maſter <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doctour</hi> Gunning.</note> 
                  <hi>Thorndike,</hi> as perſons <hi>that would ſeduce Engliſh ſubjects to Popery.</hi> And what are your Proofs? Forſooth Doctour <hi>Gunning</hi> has preached before the King, and ſince printed, and beyond your skill to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, has demonſtrated <hi>that the Lent</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:205240:20"/> 
                  <hi>faſt is an Apostolical Inſtitution.</hi> Where lies the Popery? It is, You ſay, againſt expreſs ſcripture. But is it therefore popery? Do no Sects contradict ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Scripture but Roman Catholicks? Behold the natural Logick of a Fanatick. However, let this expreſs ſcripture be produc'd. <hi>Non liquet,</hi> either in your Text or Margin. Well at leaſt, ſay You, <hi>it is againſt an Act of Parliament.</hi> Let me ask You and Your fellowes a Queſtion. Will You be content to ſtand to all <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> both as to their Prefaces and Clauſes, as Declarations of Faith: and this under the penalty of being eſteemed Papiſts: Then I here denounce You a Papiſt: For has not the whole <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Engliſh Church been ratified by Acts of parliament? But what will You ſay to an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> that has declared, and like a Heretick burnt Your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as a damned, trayterous conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie? Take heed therefore You be not found your ſelf a papiſt. As for the Lent faſt, You know that by the Lawes of the Kingdom Biſhops are appointed the exacters and diſpenſers of the <hi>Obſervance of Lent:</hi> which ſhewes it to be eſteemed an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical obſervance</hi> as well as <hi>Civil,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:205240:20"/> So that I believe Dr. <hi>Gunning</hi> is in little danger from your charge.</p>
               <p n="15">15. God ſend Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> as good a deliverance: For his Charge conſiſts <note place="margin">M. Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike.</note> of more then one, or two, or three points of Accuſation: and every one of them ſeems to have an air of popery. Let them be examined. Firſt, ſay you, <hi>he tells us in print that the Pope is not Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ.</hi> Item, <hi>That Papists are not Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Item by conſequence, <hi>that all are Schiſmaticks who upon that ſcore do refuſe Communion with them.</hi> Theſe are terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble points againſt good Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike:</hi> Yet, alas, not all his popery nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="16">16. A time was when ſuch as You, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> could both undoe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Engliſh ſubjects meerly upon an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of Popery,</hi> without <hi>proofe.</hi> God be thanked it is otherwiſe now. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore You ought at leaſt to have produced ſome proofes that theſe Aſſertions are direct popery. But not having done it: let me adviſe you what kind of proofes will be expected. You muſt know therefore that it is a Law of the Engliſh Church, <hi>that whatſoever is found in the Antient Canons, and is not expreſsly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by Eccleſiastical Authority in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205240:21"/> 
                  <hi>is to be eſteemed still in force.</hi> And common ſence and reaſon will tell you, that before you can by ſuch allegations as theſe prove any one to have deſerted the Engliſh Churches doctrine, and be turned a papiſt, you muſt produce ſome Authentick Declaration of this Church by which the Pope is decided to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and the Papiſts, Idolaters. But that is impoſſible for you to do. You will perhaps, to little purpoſe, cite the names of certain <hi>Calvinistical Writers,</hi> that, as you, hypocritically called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Engliſh Proteſtants: but withall you will take notice that all very Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants have laughed at them, ſome have been angry, and demonſtrated the direct Negative. If you were a live member of the Engliſh Church, you would know that the Engliſh Church would be no Church if the Pope were Antichriſt, and the Papiſts, Idolaters. For would you acknowledg that to be a Church that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes her whole Authority and Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction from Antichriſt and Idolaters? Is ſhe not rather a member and abortive of Antichriſt? This is plain reaſon Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw:</hi> and conſequently the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is undeniable, <hi>That all are ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks who upon that ſcore do refuſe commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Roman Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:205240:21"/> 17. You proceed againſt Mr. <hi>Thorndike, He inſinuates,</hi> ſay you, <hi>that we may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pray for the Dead.</hi> Your proof, I told you, that this is againſt Proteſtancy, muſt be to ſhew where the Engliſh Church has repealed the Antient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons commanding <hi>Prayer for the Dead.</hi> That will be a hard task. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary You your ſelves object againſt the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> that there is a clauſe in it, that not only inſinuates it to be lawful, but actually exerciſes <hi>prayer for the dead.</hi> And you know that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the time of the four firſt General Counſels (received in <hi>England)</hi> above twelve hundred years ago your Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were by the Univerſal Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Hereticks for denying it. Yea moreover that there was never extant any Liturgy or Miſſal in the Church of Chriſt, <hi>Eaſtern</hi> or <hi>Weſtern,</hi> wherein there were not <hi>prayers for the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. You go on. Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> againſt the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaies, <hi>That we may expect ſome benefit by the prayers of ſouls departed</hi> (I ſuppoſe, <hi>holy ſoules</hi> are meant.) Where does the Church of <hi>England</hi> contradict this? nay more, except you will acknowledg your ſelf to be a <hi>Socinian,</hi> and deny that the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205240:22"/> ſouls of dead perſons have any ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence at all with perception, and uſe of rational faculties, you your ſelf will not be ſo ſhameleſs as to deny what you here lay to Mr. <hi>Thorndikes</hi> charge. For I know none that call themſelves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, except <hi>Socinians,</hi> but acknowledg that the glorified Saints do pray at leaſt in general for the Church Militant. Now if they all do pray for us all, will you not permit us to expect ſome benefit by their prayers? Muſt we maintain that all their prayers are to no purpoſe? O but you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, <hi>That this in time may eaſily be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to our praying unto them.</hi> As for this inference which is not your defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, but only your own, give me leave to tell you: That if you believe that the Saints pray for the Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, it would be no hard matter by one <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> to oblige you to acknowledge that we may pray to God that he would hear and grant their prayers, making them beneficial to us. And now ſearch all the Solemn Offices and Miſſals of the Roman Church mark the prayers that occurrs every <hi>Saints Feaſt,</hi> you will find no other formes but ſuch as that: The prayer is alwayes directed to God alone immediately, and he is deſired to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205240:22"/> grant us ſuch and ſuch bleſſings by the interceſſion of ſuch Saints. And if in leſs ſolemne Devotions, as <hi>Litanies, Antiphons,</hi> &amp;c. we ſay, <hi>Sancte Maria, Sancte Michael, Sancte Petre, ora pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis:</hi> we are by the Church obliged to no other meaning then as before: and we imitate expreſs Scripture, <hi>Laudate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um omnes Angeli ejus, omnes Sancti ejus,</hi> &amp;c. Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> will aſſure you that our prayers to Saints is only <hi>prier pour prier,</hi> a devout wiſhing that they would pray for us: And truly for my part I do heartily wiſh all the Saints in heaven to intercede in their prayers with God, that he would vouchſafe to give you (and us all) a ſincere love both to truth and peace.</p>
               <p n="19">19. I have reſerved your moſt crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal charge till the laſt, which you thus expreſs, <hi>If it be not the intent of ſome to returne into Aegypt, I cannot imagine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
                  <hi>what means the crying up of that great</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>of the Papists, the Churches authority, and making that the ſole interpreter of Scripture.</hi> What Religion can you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be of, and talk thus? You in your own perſon, ſtanding alone, are not a Church. If you be but one member of a Church, what ever it be, as long as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205240:23"/> you are ſo, you are ſubject to it, it muſt have Authority over you: the Spirit of one Prophet muſt be ſubject to an aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Prophets are you an Independent? much freedom is implyed in that Title: yet I believe your Lay Church will think it has authority enough to oblige you not to interpret Scripture for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of that court of Inquiſition, the Claſſes of the Presbytery. Are you a Presbyterian? Your private reaſon ſhall be yoaked and chained with bonds ſtrong enough, and heavy enough to keep it from ſtirring to the prejudice of the Holy brethren and Siſters. But you will needs call your ſelf an Engliſh Proteſtant, and yet will dare to revile all the Authority in your Church, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proteſting that it ſhall not interpret Scripture for you: Your private reaſon ſhall over-maſter it. Unleſs it confeſſe it ſelf to be no Church, that is, to have no Authority to oblige its members to receive the ſence of ſcripture from her, you will be revenged by bellowing aloud <hi>This is the crying up of the great</hi> Diana <hi>of the Papists.</hi> Truly I muſt needs ſay, the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a very patient Church, if ſhe ſuffer you to ſpeak this <hi>Bedlam</hi> language and injoy a Benefice too.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:205240:23"/> 20. But you do well, though you mean very ill, when you call this the <hi>Diana of the Papiſts:</hi> Since you imply that a true obliging Authority, if any where, can only be found in the Catholick Church. As for Sects that have no Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Ordination for ſuch to aſſume Authority and Jurisdiction in matters of Religion, is ridiculous even to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence: for it implies, that to be men which have an ordinary uſe of reaſon, is a ſufficient qualification to become Eccleſiaſtical Teachers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours. The Clergy of <hi>England</hi> challenging a lawful Ordination, have ſome pretenſion to a real Authority: and if they could juſtify themſelves free from the guilt of Schiſme, even we Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks could not deny but their Authority would oblige in conſcience, and under the penaltie of damnation, becauſe then it would be an Authority participating that of the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and acting in union with it But of this ſomewhat more in the laſt part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="21">21. I do apprehend, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> that if you make any reply to this, you will, inſtead of ſpeaking to the purpoſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to aggravate the cauſe of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205240:24"/> 
                  <hi>Gunning</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi> by ſaying at adventure, that there is a ſecret intelligence between the Papiſts and them, and that they do mutually main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain one anothers quarrells. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide I am not without ſuſpicion that ſome even of my own belief and Church, will think that it did not become a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike to buſy himſelf with juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the writings of proteſtants, eſpecially when he endeavours to ſhew that ſuch Writers are no Catholicks, though the particular points taught by them be real Catholick verities.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Now to both theſe I muſt ſay, that I never had the happineſs to know or ſee either Doctour <hi>Gunning</hi> or Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike:</hi> never was there any meſſage or intelligence between us. But my only Motive to write as I have done, was to comply with that precept of God <hi>(Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem &amp; veritatem diligite)</hi> Love peace and Truth. As a true faithful Engliſh ſubject, I could not ſee ſo profeſſed a diſturber of peace without reproving him. As a catholick I could never hope (what I am bound to deſire and aim at) that both truth and peace would find admittance into <hi>England</hi> by any endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours either of Proteſtants or Catholicks
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:205240:24"/> till it was apparent what the true grounds of our ſeparation are: and this never will be known till other Sects be made to bluſh, when they impudently and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciouſly both to the Church and State, call themſelves Engliſh proteſtants, and pretend to be judges of what is to be eſteemed in the Engliſh Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="23">23. Therefore for a concluſion of this argument touching your charge againſt Dr. <hi>Gunning</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi> I will once more proteſt, that unleſs either the Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Authority do in time provide againſt ſuch writers as you, the whole Kingdom in a very ſhort ſpace will be in iminent danger to become a mere <hi>Babel.</hi> For if it ſhall be permitted to ſuch men, to defame any Engliſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour or Writer that ſhall not conſpire in all the furious poſitions of Presbyterians, Independents, &amp;c. againſt the Catholick Church, there will not be a Biſhop or ſober Divine in <hi>England</hi> that will not be at your mercy, both for his fame and ſubſiſtence, nay his life alſo, when you can either raiſe a tumult, or which is more dreadful, a <hi>new Tribunal of Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:205240:25"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Mr.</hi> Bagſhaws <hi>attempt to render only the Roman Catholick Subjects, in an incapacity of Toleration is in it ſelf most groundleſs, and in his mouth moſt ridiculouſly malicious.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. WEE poor Roman Catholicks could not but be ſtrangely ſurpriſed to ſee ſuch a Proteſtant of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as you Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> are, to become our Advocat, and to beg our pardon ſaying, <q rend="margQuotes"> How ill an opinion ſoever I have both of the Papiſts Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <note place="margin">Preface.</note> and of the unchriſtian waies they take to propagate it, yet far be it from me to wiſh, that amongſt us they may ſuffer the ſame hard meaſure, which I know by their Principles, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready to inflict. For ſo much do I deſire their converſion (which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſincere, unleſs it be voluntary and unconſtrained) and ſo little fear their power of ſeducing (ſince their greateſt ſtrength lies in the ignorance of their followers, rather then in the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205240:25"/> cunning of their guides) that I hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh all penal Lawes againſt them were utterly taken away: For I never yet ſaw any Argument that could clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evince, why any ſort of men who would profeſs a peaceable ſubjection unto the Civil Government, might not in all their Civil Rights be protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. What a kind wiſh is here, and a reaſon for it truly unanſwerable? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed here is Charity, a point too high to be believed ſincere. Therefore to the end your Charity may be rational, do <hi>not deprecate the inflicting of all puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any, if you can indeed prove that by the Principles of their Religion they are obliged to inflict the like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on others.</hi> As for our Principles, we proteſt unto you they are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent in this point. Laws indeed have oft been made in <hi>Catholick Countries</hi> very ſevere againſt thoſe that the Church calls <hi>Hereticks.</hi> But they are none of the Churches laws: they were not enacted by <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> but by Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Governours only. You know that by the Canons of the Church ever in force, the Clergy under penalty of <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularity</hi> are forbidden to have any
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205240:26"/> hand, either by Counſel or otherwiſe, in blood. And whatſoever Laws have been or ſhall be made by <hi>Catholick Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Governours,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as reach to blood, if the Motive of them hath been pure Opinions of the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not prejudicial to Government, or any thing except a prudent mean to prevent Sedition or Rebellions juſtly apprehended, we aſſure you they are not made by the Principles of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, but againſt them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You will object the <hi>Spaniſh Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi> But withall be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that almoſt all the Catholick King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in <hi>Europe</hi> beſides do abhorr the cruelty of that <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten declared they will ſuffer the utmoſt extremities, rather than admit it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Charity of yours therefore was too exceſſive to be long-liv'd, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to be eſteem'd ſincere: for you preſently repent and revoke it, whilſt immediatly after you add, <q rend="margQuotes"> I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs there are two things which do much difference the caſe of the Papiſts from that of any other Religious Sect <note place="margin">Preface.</note> this day in the World, and which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Toleration of them very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, if not unwarrantable.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:205240:26"/> 5. How was it poſſible for one that wrote this cruel paſſage, not preſently to blot out what with the ſame ink he had written immediatly before? The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>State</hi> are little beholding to you, when you wiſh that may be done, which is both <hi>very unſafe and unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table:</hi> and beſides, that may be done for <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> which you ſay <hi>are the only Religous Sect in the World, which it is both very unſafe and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable to tolerate:</hi> you except not even the <hi>Fifth-Monarchiſts,</hi> whoſe Religion forbids ſubjection to all Civil Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours whatſoever, and commands by Fire and Sword to erect their new ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kingdom of Chriſt, which is to laſt <hi>a thouſand years.</hi> Let but Papiſts be excluded, and all the monſters of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> are welcom to Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw:</hi> Yet he muſt know that if there had been no Papiſts in the World, no other Sect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us had ever heard of Chriſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the mercies of a Presbyterian (or Independent, I know not whether) how cruel they are.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And all this he writes to prevent the benignity of Proteſtants, which he ſuſpects may in ſome meaſure be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as well to <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205240:27"/> ſuffered with them, as to his own party that ſtill grieve they had not ſwallowed up both. He forgets what a converted criminal (as if it were ſome honeſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſt,</hi> or <hi>Quaker,</hi> one that had been, but now is no longer, a <hi>murderer</hi> and <hi>ſeditious</hi> perſon) ſaid to his obdurat companion, <hi>Dost thou not fear God, ſince thou art in the ſame condemnation? And we indeed juſtly: But theſe Men what have they done?</hi> But we ſhould not much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that his perſwaſion ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with perſons that ſure ſhould now know us both, were it not that (by what unlucky ſtar we are ignorant) a perſwaſion has entred the minds of not a few among them, that there is a ſecret intelligence and Union of intereſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Roman Catholicks and all our Sects, even to <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and that they do all joyntly conſpire againſt <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants.</hi> This opinion is imbibed by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of prudence, and otherwiſe well diſpoſed to contribute to the eaſe and comfort of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> were it not that the proofs of this accuſation are ſaid to be unanſwerable. Many Prieſts ſay they, are known to have been buſie in <hi>Cromwels Army:</hi> and even of late ſome <hi>Catholicks</hi> have ſided with Presbyterians, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:205240:27"/> 7. Now what is left for diſtreſſed <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Catholicks</hi> to do in this caſe? <hi>Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> to the contrary, will not ſerve. Writings of this nature, if they be read by ſuch, are ſlighted. <hi>Quid verba audimus</hi> (ſay they) <hi>cum facta videmus?</hi> But if they ſee them, let the ſtate ſee them too: Let ſome delinquents be produced. No: yet the thing is certainly true. But how comes this ttuth known to <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants?</hi> Have the <hi>Sectaries</hi> diſcovered it? It is hard that their teſtimony ſhould be taken: and though their profeſſed ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred be notorious, it is unlikely they would forfeit their priviledge by the <hi>Act of Indemnity,</hi> meerly to do miſchief to others. Are they Catholicks that have diſcovered this? They may eaſily be brought to a tryal: no Troops need be employed to apprehend them. And an unanſwerable way of juſtifying the paſt ſeverity of the State againſt us all, would be the arraignment of them, in caſe they can accuſe any that have inſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unlawful principles or encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into them. If all the ſeveral bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Eccleſiaſticks be not able to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie both their Religion and practiſe, we renounce all mercy. But let it be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſome Prieſts were in <hi>Cromwells</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:205240:28"/> Army: who were they? Either ſenſual Apoſtates, or I am loath to ſay who, and they perhaps with a mind to ſerve the King: Or in caſe it ſhould happen, as poſſibly it may, that three or four raſh perſons, out of a tender affection and devotion to one party among Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, whoſe excluſion they fear, to prevent that, ſhould enter into any pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe without commiſſion even of that party it ſelf, hoping that ſuch an Act of theirs would be imputed to all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and by that means hinder their Friends from being treated more ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then all the reſt; would not Juſtice it ſelf complain, if even that party ſhould ſuffer for the raſh miſdemeanours of a few: but Juſtice would forſake the earth, if all the whole innocent body ſhould be made a ſacrifice for a crime ſo committed. It is a hard condition we are in: We actually ſuffer as if we were guilty of a crime, and are forced to gueſs what that crime (utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to our ſelves) can be ſuppoſed to be. All that can be ſaid in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent circumſtances muſt be, That if in reality we can be proved deſervedly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to a condemnation upon this charge, both the preſent and future
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205240:28"/> Age ought to ſtigmatize us and our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, as perſons not only in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree criminal, but as ſuch who in a blind frenzy, after they had by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all extremities from powerful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies twenty Years together for their Soveraign, obtained a ſufficient reward in being eſteemed by him conſtantly Loyal Subjects, and (as their hopes were) had withal ſufficiently freed their Religion from the ſcandal of infidelitie: afterwards when his <hi>Majesty</hi> was reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his power, and treated them with a mercy never before experienced by them, yea moreover when the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lords in Parliament after a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearing of their defence, gave them hopes of future favour, juſt then they deſerted their Loyalty to the King: and entred into a combination with enemies alwaies implacable to themſelves, and at a time when thoſe Enemies had all power taken from them. This would be a complication of all crimes in one, a Treaſon joyned with the moſt prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ingratitude, moſt ſcandalous impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, moſt barbarous inhumanity, and moſt brutiſh ſtupidity that ever was.</p>
               <p n="8">8. But Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> (who, I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, does not ſuſpect us, nay knowes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205240:29"/> we are not guilty of this crime) calls me to hear his Reaſons why <hi>Papists alone ſhould be ill-treated:</hi> and I obey. You ſay, <hi>Sir, you have more then one reaſon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
                  <hi>which does difference the caſe of Papists from all other Sects, &amp;c.</hi> If this be true, then You had not ſo much as half a reaſon to <hi>wiſh ſincerely that the penal Statutes ſhould be taken from them:</hi> Nay that unlawful wiſh deſerved puniſhment.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Let us ſee theſe Your evincing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. <hi>One is,</hi> ſay You, <hi>their depending upon and owning a forraign power, &amp;c.</hi> If you had ſtopped at theſe words, we ſhould have found no reply. For we confeſs, <hi>ſuch a power we depend upon and own;</hi> but we utterly deny that that ſhould put us in a worſe condition then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For if that Power be purely ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, that is, of a quite different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not in the leaſt degree preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the Kings Civil Power, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obliging thoſe that acknowledg it, faithfully to obey the King, the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſurely ought to be no hindrance to a Toleration. If you think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then I muſt tell You that no Sect of Chriſtians whatſoever ought to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in <hi>England.</hi> For let me ask You (who ever you are, whether <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:205240:29"/> 
                  <hi>Independent, Anabaptist, Quaker,</hi> or even <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant)</hi> Do not you, and all of Your perſwaſion with You, depend upon and own a power diſtinct from his Majeſties Civil power, I mean, a power meerly Spirituall, or Paſtoral, not ſubordinate to the Kings, but to which the King himſelf, if he be of your Religion, ought to be ſubject, as being no Paſtour, but a Sheep, no Teacher, but a Hearer; no adminiſtrer of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but a receiver; no Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catour, but lyable himſelf, as all Chriſts flock are when they demerit it, to have Eccleſiaſtical cenſures inflicted on him? Such a power, I am ſure, you all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge: And no other power do Roman Catholicks depend upon or own. Be not then ſo manifeſtly, ſo affectedly partial, as to alledge that to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and deſtruction of Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks only, which muſt as well exclude all Chriſtians out of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. But it is a forreign power, You ſay, that Papiſts depend upon and own, and this word <hi>Forreign</hi> makes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. It does indeed: But the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is, I ſuppoſe, much to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage both of the King and Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks too. For tell me for Gods ſake
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:205240:30"/> ſince there is indeed a ſpiritual power from which Princes themſelves ought not to be exempted, nor can free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it without infinite prejudice to their own ſouls, is it not more for their temporal peace and ſecurity that this Spiritual power ſhould reſide in one ſingle perſon that uſually is both learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſcreet, and withal is a thouſand miles removed from our King, then in many thouſands within his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, not all of them Angels, that if they have a mind to do him a miſchief, have all the means and opportunities imaginable? The <hi>King of France</hi> eſteems it a great priviledge granted him in a <hi>Concordate</hi> by the Pope, that no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Biſhop ſhould have power in any caſe to excommunicate him: this power being reſerved by the Pope alone.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Thefore you do very well when for an eſcape to your ſelves You add, but very ill, when moſt calumniouſly to us You add, <q rend="margQuotes"> That Catholicks depend upon and own ſuch a power which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinion of their teachers <note place="margin">Preface.</note> can when he pleaſes diſpenſe with them for, and releaſe them from their moſt ſacred engagements: So that a State can have no ſecurity, but that when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:205240:30"/> ever they have opportunity they will endeavour a change: And their preſent peaceableneſs may juſtly be attributed merely to their want of ſtrength: which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is not aſhamed to ſay was the ſole cauſe why the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were content to ſuffer without reſiſtance. From which poſition what can follow, but that it concerns the wiſdome and policy of every State to keep thoſe under, whom as to Temporal Subjection it cannot confide in.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Imperet tibi Dominus.</hi> Here the world ſees the charity of a Presbyterian, &amp;c. in its natural colours. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity ſo divinely commended by <hi>St. Paul</hi> has theſe qualities, <hi>Non cogitat malum, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes"> It thinks no ill: It does not rejoyce in iniquitie, but rejoyces <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> with the truth: It ſuffers all things; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves all things, it hopes all things. But this mans new faſhioned charity thinks nothing but ill of all divided from his intereſts. It rejoyces only when any of them fall into any defects, and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces at their well doing. It ſuffers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whatſoever good they promiſe it believes nothing, it hopes nothing.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. But truly, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> You have made choice of a moſt unſeaſonable time
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:205240:31"/> to vomit forth theſe moſt ſpightful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes againſt Catholicks, with any hope they ſhould be believed. In the laſt age indeed when the criminous Writings and practiſes of four or five Catholicks of one peculiar Order had juſtly incenſed the State, and no way was afforded to all the reſt publickly to defend themſelves from an imputation of concurring with, and holding the wicked principles of a few Traytours, ſuch a bloody accuſation as this might perhaps find entrance into the minds of ſome few unwary perſons. But now when ſuch practiſes and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples have been he artily diſavowed by all ſorts of Catholicks: When the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Catholick Lords, have in the name of the whole body of the Catholicks, before a moſt glorious Tribunal made moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident proteſtations of an Eternal fidelity to the King, and of <hi>renouncing all depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on a forreign Authority that can any way be prejudicial to him:</hi> When ſo many profeſſions have been printed by ſeveral ſorts of Catholicks declaring, <hi>That no power upon earth can abſolve them from their moſt neceſſary &amp; natural Allegiance, nor ſo much as free them from the Obligation of any Promiſe or Engagement made to any private perſon:</hi> When his Majeſty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:205240:31"/> has honoured his Catholick ſubjects with ſuch a confidence in their Loyalty and ſincerity, as to truſt his life into their hands, when ſome (Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> knows who) ſought and hunted after that moſt pretious life; Laſtly when for the ſpace of twenty years a <hi>fiery tryall</hi> has paſſed upon the fidelity of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and never could diminiſh it: Now, I ſay, after all this to hear this accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation againſt them, out of ſuch a mouth as Mr. <hi>Bagſhaws,</hi> that <hi>they depend on a Power that can releaſe them from their moſt ſacred engagements,</hi> is beyond all ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. What name can be found out worthily to expreſs ſuch a ſhameleſsneſs in a Presbyterian or Independent, none of whoſe party ever aſſiſted, but rather uſed all their power and skill to ruine the King, and after their Indemnity not one has appeared to make a publick promiſe of dealing better with him for the future? Who can with patience hear ſuch an one, <q rend="margQuotes">tell the State, that it is concerned in wiſdom and policy to keep Roman Catholicks under, whom as to temporal ſubjection it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confide in, when as not any one of them diſſerved the ſtate, but many</q> thouſands have loſt their lives, and far
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:205240:32"/> more (almoſt all) are ruined in their eſtates for their fidelity only; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over to ſhew that this Fidelity was a Duty of their Religion, have and ever will be ready to give all ſecurity of peaceable obedience and ſincere integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that Words or Actions can confirme? What can You expect, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> ſhould be the fruit of ſuch a paſſage as this in a Book of Yours, but a guilty bluſhing in Your own party, indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in loyal Proteſtants to hear ſuch as You become accuſers in ſuch a cauſe as this, and joy in Roman Catholicks, to ſee that none have of late taxed them as perſons not to be confided in, but ſuch <hi>old confiding men,</hi> as after oathes of Fidelity have taken the Covenant and Engagements worſe then that, and but for an Act of <hi>Oblivion, &amp;c.</hi> would in <hi>Weſtminster-Hall</hi> hear, and not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to anſwer a far heavier accuſation then this?</p>
               <p n="14">14. There are but two Oaths by the State accounted tryals of an Engliſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects fidelity, that of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and of <hi>Allegiance.</hi> If the former were but ſo expreſſed as to require an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Civil Supremacy in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty only, excluſively to the Pope: And
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:205240:32"/> if the unfortunate word, <hi>Heretical</hi> were left out of the other, no honeſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick would deſire to be allowed the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of a ſubject if he refuſed either. And more then this, not any one Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, Presbyterian, or whoſoever he be that freely takes them, can intend by them. For not any of theſe will ſay that the Catholick Church of any Age has defind this Aſſertion to be Heretical, <hi>That Princes excommunicated or deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed or murdered by their Subjects:</hi> It being an aſſertion they never dream'd of: Neither will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe that make no ſcruples at ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Oathes, allow a ſpirituall power, much leſs a Supremacy in that power to the King. So that it is evident that Catholicks are expoſed to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of ſufferings for not taking oaths in the full importance of whoſe ſence they agree with all thoſe by whom they are perſecuted.</p>
               <p n="15">15. But truly now, fince the State has moſt graciouſly been pleaſed to give a publick hearing to the Catholicks, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by the Tongues of the Catholick Lords, &amp;c. who have againſt all poſſible objections maintained the innocence of our Religion in the point of Fidelity:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205240:33"/> And ſince it has been a general aſſevera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Magiſtrates and the State, that they never had any intention to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way any mans life merely for his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and conſcience, as long as he was free from practiſing ſedition: Me thinks hereafter our <hi>Justitiae Sacerdotes,</hi> the Reverend Judges ſhould find a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to perſwade their conſciences to permit their tongues to pronounce a condemnation, as for treaſon, againſt any Engliſh ſubject, meerly for having a ſcruple in an Oath to bring forth the word Heretical, he being at the ſame time ready to acknowledge, as due to the King, all the authority and right that the Judge himſelf does, when he condemns him for a traytour.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Therefore, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> if You would perſwade the State that it cannot confide in Catholicks, You muſt ſtudy ſome other motives: For <hi>we heartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the acknowledgment of any power that can diſpence with us, or releaſe us of our Engagements to his Majesty.</hi> They are none of our teachers that hold ſuch opinions. And what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaies, <hi>That the ſole cauſe why the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were content to ſuffer without reſiſtance was their want of power,</hi> we abhor, as a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:205240:33"/> ſpeech blaſphemous to the Holy Martyrs, and ſcandalous to the Church. Yet let me tell You, this was a Doctrine that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> might have learnt from Your Fore-fathers the antient <hi>Puritans,</hi> for out of them it is that Archbiſhop <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft</hi> quotes ſuch unchriſtian ſayings and words, as this for one, <q rend="margQuotes"> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to be ſubject and obedient to <note place="margin">Bancroft <hi>in Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions p.</hi> 17</note> Princes, did write this in the infancie of the Church: there were but few Chriſtians then, and not many of them rich, or of ability, ſo as they were not for ſuch a purpoſe. As if a man ſhould write to ſuch Chriſtians as are under the <hi>Turk,</hi> in ſubſtance poor, in cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage feeble, in ſtrength unarm'd, in number few, and generally ſubject to all kind of injuries, would he not write as <hi>Paul</hi> did? So as the Apoſtle did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the men he wrote unto, and his words are not to be extended to the body or people of a Common wealth or whole City. For imagine that <hi>Paul</hi> were now alive, &amp;c. and that there were ſuch Kings as would have their becks ſtand for Laws, as cared neither for God nor man, &amp;c. what would he write of ſuch to the Church? Surely except he would deſſent from himſelf,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205240:34"/> he would ſay, that he accounteth not ſuch for Magiſtrates, &amp;c, he would leave them to their ſubjects to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. What think You of this Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw?</hi> Yet I will not accuſe You of hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame. Nay more, though I can demonſtrate tuat there's not a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or City in Chriſtendom into which Your Sect or Religion ever entred by any other waies but ſedition and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, witneſs <hi>France, Geneva, Holland,</hi> ſeveral States in <hi>Germany, Switzerland, Scotland,</hi> and (for almoſt twenty Years ſpace) <hi>England,</hi> yet if You would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that abominable principle, <hi>That it is lawful to defend Religion by arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a lawful Prince,</hi> I ſhould have a ſcruple to ſay, that <hi>a State cannot ſafely or warrantably confide in you,</hi> as You have moſt unjuſtly ſaid againſt Roman Catholicks, taking advantage from one or two Writers generally diſallowed by us, though You can not name any one City or Country in Chriſtendom into which Catholick Religion ever entred but by ſuffering.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Do not therefore endeavour to make all Catholicks anſwerable for the wicked aſſertions of a few Authors, when
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205240:34"/> you know they have been condemned by whole Kingdoms. You have eyes ſharp enough to ſpy even in the Catholick Church our ſort of Presbyterians and Independents, Yea even Quakers too: If any ſuch be in <hi>England,</hi> the State may eaſily convert them. However God be thanked their teachings are out of faſhion: and I would to God they diſpleaſed You as much as they do us. You know we can lay to your charge ten ſeditious Authours for one: and which is mainly (indeed, only) conſiderable, You are not able to produce one of your party that has condemned their horribly Rebellious principles. And as to the point of defending Religion by Arms, if by a Reply You will ſummon me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the particular paſſages, I will at large informe You, that during the reign of the laſt King of <hi>France,</hi> there was by his order propoſed to an Aſſembly of Catholick Biſhops this Queſtion or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, <q rend="margQuotes"> If it were ſuppoſed that the King of <hi>France</hi> became <hi>Mahumetan,</hi> and by his power endeavoured to force his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to that infidelity, Whether they might lawfully, according to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſtianity, by arms againſt their Soveraign reſiſt ſuch an attempt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205240:35"/> of his?</q> To which Queſtion the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous anſwer of the Biſhops was, <q rend="margQuotes"> That ſuch a reſiſtance would be unlawful: ſince Chriſtian Religion allowed no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of maintaining the faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lawful Soveraigns, but prayers, tears and ſuffering.</q> When will <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> be ſo happy as to ſee ſuch a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to proceed from a Synod of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, &amp;c. It would be ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to ſee but one, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> publiſh a little book to that purpoſe. Never cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly was there a more ſeaſonable time then now. That would be a powerful expedient to imprint the Act of Oblivion in the very hearts of all Engliſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: And till ſome ſuch thing be done, <hi>Quis Caelum terris non miſceat</hi> to read from ſuch an one as Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi>'s pen a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Fidelity to the King, and a warning given to the State, who the only perſons are not fit to be confided in?</p>
               <p n="19">19. You add, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw, But could our Papiſts in</hi> England <hi>give ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their hearty diſowning ſuch an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious Tenet, yet there is another thing,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What ſay You Sir; <hi>Could the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts?</hi> Why, have they not? Is their an ear in <hi>England</hi> that can perceive ſence, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:205240:35"/> has not heard what a profeſſion was made by the Catholick Lords in the Houſe of Peers? Is there an eye that can read, and has not ſeen their printed Declarations in which that irreligious Tenet was confidently, clearly and heartily Diſavowed? They have, do, and will proteſt, that if they be not ready to give all poſſible ſecurity of diſavow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, and all other Principles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to Authority, Juſtice, and Peace, it would neither be prudence in his Majeſty, nor a juſt care of his Kingdomes welfare, to tolerate them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Subjects. What would you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more?</p>
               <p n="20">20. If You think, or however, if You be reſolved to ſay, though You do not think ſo, that we <hi>lye</hi> when we both make ſuch proteſtations, and withall offer to confirme them by Oathes, You will put us into ſome puzzle how to give You ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. Yet in order thereto, even to You that perhaps are unwilling to be ſatisfied, we tell You this. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but know that Catholick Religion utterly forbids all <hi>lying,</hi> and above all, <hi>Perjury.</hi> If therefore You will judge, that neither the Proteſtations, nor Oaths of Catholicks, are to be credited, you
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:205240:36"/> will condemn the State of want of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in contriving Oathes for tryals of their Fidelity: and moreover you muſt needs eſteem us the moſt imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Lyars in the World, that is, ſuch as only lye when it is for our diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. If we durſt lye, we would much rather chuſe to lye by taking the Oathes in the formes as they are expreſſed, then make <hi>voluntary falſe proteſtations</hi> of the ſame duty that the oaths require: becauſe by taking the Oathes we ſhould free our ſelves oftimes from the loſs of our Eſtates, and ſometimes of our lives: whereas by ſuch Voluntary proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we cannot challenge any temporal commodity: nay perhaps we anger thoſe, that take it worſe from us that we prove our ſelves good ſubjects, then they would, if we had been ill ones. This is all I can at preſent ſay to ſuch a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If this ſatisfy not, God mend thoſe that are in fault.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Let us now ſee Your ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why only Papiſts muſt not be tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted though they were never ſo good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. That You deliver in theſe words. <q rend="margQuotes"> There is another thing practiſed by <note place="margin">Preface.</note> them, which makes it highly queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, whether a Kingdom profeſſing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:205240:36"/> Chriſtianity ought to tolerate them in, &amp; that is their Worſhipping of Images: which is a ſin ſo contrary to the expreſs letter of the Divine Law, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the common ſence and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all men, that God puniſhed it ſeverely even in the Heathen Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as well as in his own people the Jewes.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. You are hard put to it, Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> to find reaſons to kill Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks. The ſaying is <hi>Furor arma;</hi> but it has put a ſtraw into Your hands, to wound us with. Yet I am likewiſe hard put to it too, how to defend my ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt even ſuch a weapon: that is, how to diſcourſe upon this point of Images with one that profeſſes he will neither accept Fathers, Councels, nor the whole Church it ſelf for an Interpreter of Scriptures, or Decider of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, but only his own private enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reaſon. It cannot be helped there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Reaſon alone muſt be judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us: You will needs have it ſo. Let reaſon then be our judge, but upon condition that You will not call that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which is againſt common ſence.</p>
               <p n="22">22. You ſay, <hi>The worſhipping of Images is a ſin repugnant to the common ſence and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Freſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:205240:37"/> 
                  <hi>reaſon of all ſober men:</hi> ſo that your common ſence and reaſon concludes, that there is not a Catholick in the world that is a ſober man, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void of common ſence and reaſon: and by conſequence, all <hi>France, Spain, Italy, Germany, Savoy, Greece, &amp;c.</hi> are but one large <hi>Bedlam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 24. Well, however give one of theſe <hi>Bedlam men</hi> leave to propoſe to ſuch a ſober man as you are, that is all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of Reaſon, ſome few Queſtions, Firſt, then ſuppoſe there were repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to you while You were thinking of other matters, or talking, a picture of our Lord hanging on the Croſſe: could you poſſibly avoid the calling to mind who our Lord was, and what he had done or ſuffered for you? And if not being able to forbid the entrance of ſuch thoughts into your mind on ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, would your reaſon dictate to you that you had done ill in changing your thoughts from the world to God, would you repent of it, asking pardon of God, and praying that ſuch a tentation might never befal you afterwards? Does your enlightned reaſon ſuggeſt this to you? Truely if it do, I believe you are of a temper of mind almoſt ſpecifically diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:205240:37"/> from all mankind beſides, and muſt change their nature before You make them of your perſwaſion, or Church. And yours is not a common ſence, if it either tell You that by Your beating down Croſſes and breaking Church windows, our good Countrymen think more of God then they did while thoſe remembrances were ſtanding: or if they think leſs, that it is better for them, to forget him.</p>
               <p n="25"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 25. To make a ſtep further, Let it be ſuppoſed that at the ſame time You ſaw before you ſeveral pictures of ſeveral perſons in quite contrary manner regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by you, as of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> of our <hi>Late Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Bradſhaw:</hi> (you are beholding to me for this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample:) Or put caſe you had in one hand a Bible and in the other the infamous ſtory of <hi>Pantagruel:</hi> does not your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence and reaſon tell you, that ſuch pictures or books force upon your mind quite contrary thoughts and affections, the which regard thoſe pictures or books not ſimply conſidered, but as repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch perſons, and containing ſuch matter? The which thoughts being juſt, and not at all harmful to you, and withal almoſt impoſſible to be avoyded, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:205240:38"/> find any reaſon why reaſon ſhould forbid them: I am ſure common ſence will not.</p>
               <p n="26"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 26. If then it be according to reaſon and common ſence, and likewiſe una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voydable to admit ſuch different thoughts: will not reaſon alſo warrant you to expreſſe outwardly by words or actions, whatſoever you may without any fault think inwardly? For my part I cannot imagine any ſcruple in this. If then I may and muſt think reverently or contemptuouſly of the Objects, I may as well ſpeak, or behave my ſelf externally after the ſame manner to them reſpectively; For whatſoever is ill or good in words or actions, is ſo likewiſe in thoughts.</p>
               <p n="27"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 27. Now to ſhew that ſuch thoughts or affections regard not the perſons only but the pictures alſo as repreſentations of ſuch perſons, ask Your own heart and You will find that You would not place S. <hi>Peters</hi> picture, or the Kings in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, diſhoneſt place. If any one ſhould ſpit upon either of them, your heart would riſe againſt him, and tempt you to ſtrike him: which it would not do, if the ſame contemptuous uſage were ſhewed to the picture of <hi>Judas</hi> or <hi>Bradſhaw.</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:205240:38"/> Now this is ſo naturally imbibed in the hearts of all mankind, that in all Kings Courts a reſpect and outward mark of reverence is required to the Chamber of preſence, or Chair of State: and a refuſal of it, much more a contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous behaviour, would be criminal. To apply this to the forementioned Books: You could not bring your reaſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit You to tear out a leafe of the Bible for an unclean uſe, as you could without the leaſt remorſe do to the ſtory of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagruel</hi> or <hi>Aeſops fables.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 28. Let us now conſider what kind of reſpect this is that we expreſs to ſuch images. Comparing the images of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and our Soveraigns together, we find that a reſpectful regard is had to both, and a contemptuous uſage of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would diſpleaſe us: Yet it is not the ſame kind of reſpect: For St. <hi>Peters</hi> image we conſider as of a man that puts us in mind of heaven and heavenly things, one highly favoured by Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, a principal Courtier in his Kingdom, and one that by his writings and example has been a great inſtrument of promoting our eternal happineſs. We do not ſo eſteem of every good King. Therefore to ſhew the difference of our
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:205240:39"/> reſpect to each, we would chooſe to give St. <hi>Peters</hi> picture a place in our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, and the Kings in our Gallery. But what names to give to theſe different reſpects is not eaſie to determine. It is plain, that which is given to the Kings picture is purely a civil reſpect: but what ſhall we call that which is given to St. <hi>Peters?</hi> If we ſay it is <hi>Religious,</hi> you will quarrel, as derogating from God. Let us therefore call it a <hi>ſacred</hi> vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or honour: For ſince all things that are appointed on purpoſe to mind us of God, of heaven and the ſalvation of our ſouls, we call them ſacred, this name may well be applyed to ſuch a picture. But moreover, becauſe there are not invented ſuch variety of names as there are things, and there are far fewer ſorts of outward poſtures of our Bodies denoting reſpect, then there are Names or Words: Hence it comes to paſs that when we would expreſs a Civil and a Sacred, yea a Religious reſpect, we are forced to uſe the ſame outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of bowing, kneeling, &amp;c. to Fathers and Magiſtrates, that we do to God himſelf: Yea we find in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Kings <hi>adored,</hi> and a proſtration of bodies paid to them. Yet for all this no
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:205240:39"/> man will ſuſpect that thereby any diſhonour was intended to God, or the Honour due only to him was paid to creatures.</p>
               <p n="29"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 29. In the next place let reaſon and common ſence give judgment of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between the reſpect that may be paid to the picture of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and that which ought to be paid to himſelf in caſe he appeared to us glorified as he is. A Divine reſpect we pay to neither, though ſometimes we uſe ſuch poſtures as we do when we pray, or worſhip God. It is then a <hi>ſacred veneration</hi> only: but yet there are ſome expreſſions of reſpect that we would uſe to the perſon, that would be ridiculous to the picture, as reverently to ſpeak to him, to beg his prayers to God for us, to ask a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="30"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 30. Our laſt Enquiry ſhall be into the difference of regard (if any there be) to our Saviours picture and S. <hi>Peters,</hi> the former repreſenting to us him that is both God and man, the latter, meerly man. However we ſhall find that the regard to both the pictures is of the ſame ſpecies and nature, that is, only <hi>ſacred:</hi> becauſe a picture we never look upon but as an inſtrument to put us in mind,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:205240:40"/> or to call to our memories an object: and therefore it being of our own frame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not capable of any reſpect beyond that which is due to ſo material, inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our a thing, what ever the object repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by it be. True it is that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal affections and thoughts occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally raiſed in our minds will be infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different, for we ſhall think upon Chriſt with Adoration, Love, Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Obedience due to God only: not ſo of St. <hi>Peter:</hi> but the pictures themſelves will be treated by us as ſacred pictures only, that deſerve a reſpect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable: And ſince it is evident they are capable of a ſinful diſreſpect, conſequently a due reſpect may be paid to them. I ſay, <hi>may be, not alwaies ought</hi> to be: for then it would never be fit to put on ones hat, &amp;c. in a room where there hangs a crucifix.</p>
               <p n="31">31. To ſumme up briefly our meaning in this whole matter: We find our minds too apt to be diſtracted from me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating on Divine things: therefore we help our ſelves by ſuch things as will call to our memories, and fix our thoughts upon Objects good for our ſouls to be thought upon: Such are holy pictures both in times of prayer and out, we find
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:205240:40"/> this benefit by them. Being ſuch ſacred things, we muſt renounce our reaſon, if we deny a reſpect may be due to them: but by honouring with an outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard a picture, we intend only to give a teſtimony what reſpect we bear to the perſon or holy thing repreſented: And though for want of variety of poſtures, we ſhew ſome part of the ſame outward Reverence to the pictures of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and our Lord, yet that ſignifies, we only venerate <hi>St. Peter</hi> as a glorious Saint, yet a creature, but that we adore Chriſt as God: And no man that ſees or knows us can think otherwiſe. So that unleſs it be a ſin to ſhew outwardly what we are oblig'd to think inwardly, there is not the leaſt fault committed.</p>
               <p n="32">32. And now Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> give me leave to acquaint You with Your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes. <hi>Firſt,</hi> this reſpect called by the Church, Honour and Veneration, which We affirme may be paid to ſacred Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, you call <hi>Worſhipping of Images,</hi> meerly to make us odious to your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Proſelytes: For Worſhip is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken to be that Honour which is due only to God, and which we abhor to give to Images. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> you give it another name more abominable,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:205240:41"/> calling it, <hi>Idolatry ſuch as God puniſhed in the worſt of Pagans.</hi> Once at leaſt in your life ſpeak your conſcience: Do you think, or only ſuſpect that we Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks do worſhip falſe Gods, and true Devils? Do we conſider our Images, as they did their Idols, to which by <hi>Magical conjurations</hi> they annexed an evil Spirit to do wonders, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort Divine worſhip from the ſeduced people? Take heed <hi>Sir</hi> how you perſiſt in ſo unjuſt a blaſphemy againſt Gods Church: A time will come that You will be called to a ſtrict account for it: it concerns you therefore to make ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</p>
               <p n="33">33. But after all this, take notice that the Catholick Church, though it declare that ſuch a veneration may fitly be given to Holy Images, as common Reaſon, and Humane nature cannot chooſe but allow: Yet it commands none to afford them but even ſo much. You may be a Roman Catholick all your life, and yet never be obliged to performe any external reſpect to an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. There is not in Catholick coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries a Groom or Kitchin-maid ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but would rather burn an Image, then afford it any honour due to God
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:205240:41"/> only. And ſhall thoſe that think thus, and do only what humane reaſon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally approves and cannot hinder, be eſteemed and publiſhed by you <hi>the only Chriſtians in the World fit to be thruſt out of all Christian Kingdomes, and executed as traytours,</hi> though otherwiſe they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged moſt faithful, peaceable men and obedient Subjects? Are you not afraid of, <hi>In quo judicio judicaveritis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicabimini?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="34">34. You ſee <hi>Sir,</hi> how ſince you will not admit of Authorities to juſtify the Beliefe and Practice of Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, but only common ſence and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I have complyed with you: And now in one word tell you, that You muſt never hope to make any ſober man believe that Roman Catholicks are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, or even faulty in the matter of Images, till You can demonſtrate, 1. <hi>That</hi> it is unlawful to make uſe of our Seeing faculty to put us in mind of God. 2. <hi>That</hi> he diſhonours the King that ſhall with reverence, bareheaded, and in a kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſture receive a Letter or Mandate that comes from him. 3. <hi>That</hi> it is a contempt of God to go through a Church with ones head uncovered. 4. And that it is unlawful, and irreligious
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:205240:42"/> to make a ſcruple of uſing a leaf of the Bible in the houſe of Office.</p>
               <p n="35">35. For a farewel I will conclude this point with a Story, the truth whereof ſeveral Gentlemen, Proteſtants too, in this Town are able to juſtify. <q rend="margQuotes"> In the year 1651. a devout <hi>Italian Friar</hi> being appointed to preach in the <hi>Great Dome</hi> at <hi>Padua,</hi> the Archbiſhop preſent, and having been informed that among his Auditors there were ſome Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that in diſcourſe had earneſtly objected (as you do) Idolatry to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, He therefore that he might occur to ſuch a ſcandal, made choice of the Doctrine concerning Images for the ſubject of a great part of his ſermon. And when he came to that point, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his hand a Crucifix, he told his hearers, That that Image did in one glance lively repreſent, even to the moſt ignorant beholder, <hi>our Lord Jeſus, God and Man,</hi> and almoſt all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his moſt bitter and accurſed death ſo patiently and willingly ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us. Thereupon with great paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Rhetorick he magnified the Love of our Lord hanging on the Croſs, earneſtly preſſing his hearers to return a proportionable Love and Duty
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:205240:42"/> to him. And during this diſcourſe, he often with great reverence and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of affection embraced and devoutly kiſſed the Crucifix. Having ſaid much to this purpoſe, after a little pauſe he purſued his Diſcourſe, telling them he could not believe or ſuſpect, that any one that had heard and ſeen what he had ſaid and done, could reaſonably imagine that he had any intention to diſhonour our Lord, by that which he had done to the Crucifix which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him, much leſs that he adored it, as if he thought it a kind of God, that he put his truſt in it, as expecting any good from it, as if (he knew not what) Divinity, Vertue or Sanctity was in that carved piece of wood. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding becauſe he had heard that ſuch a ſcandalous imputation was by ſome miſperſwaded perſons laid on the Church, he would then and there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive them. Thereupon he ſpit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Crucifix, threw it ſcornfully to the ground, and trampled it under his feet.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="36">36. You ſee, Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> what kind of Idolaters the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are. Againſt this <hi>Idolatry,</hi> let us ſee what <hi>expreſs Scripture</hi> you can produce. This is the great
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:205240:43"/> 
                  <hi>crime,</hi> for which there can be no expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but <hi>oppreſſions, empriſonments</hi> and <hi>Gallowſes.</hi> Now if what hath been here ſaid give you no ſatisfaction, in caſe you have a mind to reply, do not practice your old way of ſnatching a phraſe or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion out of a ſingle <hi>Authour,</hi> a <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> or <hi>Controvertist,</hi> and making the whole Church anſwerable for one mans indeſcretion. But ſearch what the Church her ſelf has declared in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and diſpute againſt that as well as you can: and be aſſured you ſhall either be anſwered, or elſe told that you are unconquerable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV. <note place="margin">VI.</note>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Mr.</hi> Bagſhaw's <hi>whole Diſcourſe against the Churches Infallibility is nothing to the purpoſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. HItherto of your Preface: Now I come to your book: which truly will afford very little buſineſſe. And in groſſe concerning your grave Diſcourſe I muſt tell you, That if you would be as merciful to our Eſtates and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:205240:43"/> our Lives as You are to this our funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Doctrine, we ſhould find You a a very commodious Adverſary: For notwithſtanding all your bluſtring You have not given this Doctrine one blow that ſmarts at all: But God bleſs us from Your Swords, and Your Sermons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Title of your book is, <hi>The great Question about the Infallibility of the Pope and Church of Rome:</hi> This Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion you undertake to determine. We are likely to have good ſtuff in a Book that miſtakes the ſubject to be diſcourſed on. You ſhould not have ſaid, <hi>The great Question about, &amp;c.</hi> but <q rend="margQuotes"> Two Queſtions, the one a great one, about the Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Roman Catholick Church: which if it be diſproved, deſtroys the foundation of that Church: the other a very little queſtion about the Popes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal infallibility, in which the Church it ſelf is not concerned at all, but only Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and a few Writers zealous for that Court.</q> And when you had ſaid this, in all reaſon, having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to triumph over Roman Catholicks, you ought not to have ſaid a word about this little, trifling, unconcerning Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but have bent all your forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Great one which was only to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:205240:44"/> 3. But You very wiſely have ſpent your whole book upon it only, though a ſubject that You your ſelf in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face confeſs, <hi>is not yet decided in the Schools amongst learned men,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, no Catholick is obliged to maintain, and conſequently no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant needs trouble himſelf about it: Nay moreover you ſay <hi>the two Councils of</hi> Baſil <hi>and</hi> Conſtance, <hi>and</hi> (in your Book) <hi>the ſixth General Council</hi> have (ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually) decided the contrary, having preferred the Authority of a Council above the Pope, which therefore may reverſe his deciſions, and actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned a Pope of Hereſie: you might have added the ſeventh and eighth Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils which ratifyed the ſame condemnation: and to them You might have joyned Pope <hi>Agathon</hi> the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> that was condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his Succeſſours Pope <hi>Leo the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> and the reſt till Pope <hi>Adrian the ſecond,</hi> who lived in the time of the eighth Council<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Why do You write Books Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> ſo confeſſedly to no purpoſe at all? And why do you trouble your ſelf about a ſubject that the Authour whom you pretend to confute, cannot himſelf
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:205240:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> believe, what ever opinion or ſuſpition he may have of it? For no Catholick can be ſaid to believe any thing as a Chriſtian Verity merely upon diſcourſe of Reaſon, or probable deduction from Scripture, but only when ſuch a verity appears either expreſsly contained in the Bible, or is formally decided by a General Council, or received by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Tradition of the Church. Now it is apparent, even out of <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> himſelf, that none of theſe wayes the Popes Infallibility has been confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Nay more, <hi>Never yet has any Pope declared that himſelf is Infallible.</hi> But you are wiſe in the midſt of folly. You write out of all danger of being confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe no body thinks himſelf touched: ſo that you have an eaſie and cheap triumph of it. Notwithſtanding by your own example I do much doubt your <hi>Honourable patron,</hi> by whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, You ſay, You wrote, finds not <note place="margin">Epiſt. Dedic.</note> his expectation anſwered; if he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any great matter: and I am ſure being very knowing and wiſe he will not believe that (as you brag) <hi>you have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Enemy, having left no Argument unanſwered:</hi> ſince evidently you have miſtaken your enemies perſon through
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:205240:45"/> your whole book, excepting only the two laſt leaves, where <hi>obiter,</hi> and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to an Objection ſuppoſed to be made by moderate and ingenuous Papiſts you make an offer to ſpeak <hi>de tribus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellis,</hi> that is, <hi>the Pope's being infallible, not in himſelf, but in and with a Councill:</hi> which though it be the only matter in queſtion, you call only a <hi>Conceit, of which you will ſpeak a little,</hi> and you keep your word, you ſay very little, and that little to no purpoſe at all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Therefore to what purpoſe ſhould any Catholick ſet pen to Paper to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you, ſince if you be never ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently confuted, you are excuſed from yielding by ſaying <hi>you have ſaid a very little,</hi> but could have ſaid more: and Catholicks are forbidden to yield, ſince they have a world of proofs to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat, the <hi>Infallibility of the Church,</hi> far more efficacious then theſe one or two Texts of Scripture called out by you for your beſt advantage. And even theſe Texts as they are produced and made uſe of by Catholicks are unanſwerable, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe that think it reaſonable to admit that to be the ſence of Scripture which all antiquity has given, which all proteſtants and all reaſonable men do.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:205240:45"/> They could not foreſee that there could ariſe a Diſputant ſo void of reaſon, as Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> to whom the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Ages of the Church, all Councils and Fathers appeared light and inconſiderable, if compared with his ſingle reaſon. Therefore till you have proved that Ground demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, that is, turned ſand into a Rock, you are not in a capacity either to object or anſwer.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And to the end you may ſet upon ſuch a work to ſome purpoſe, I pray pleaſe to enquire out a Book called <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omologeſis,</hi> or <hi>Motives of the Converſion &amp;c.</hi> where your great <hi>Laniſta</hi> Mr. <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths</hi> reaſons for ſuch a poſition are pretended to be anſwered; and in an Appendix to that Book You will find an <hi>Examination of the Fundamental Grounds of my Lord</hi> Faulklands <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> on that Subject. Theſe are the men you brag of in Your Preface as your great Patrons, that is indeed, ſuch Proteſtants as you are, that lay ſuch grounds as utterly demoliſh the whole ſtructure of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh church, denying that any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon Earth can oblige any man. And this very thing, I mean, the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the Church of England</hi> you <note place="margin">Preface.</note>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:205240:46"/> your ſelf confeſſe in your Preface to have <note place="margin">Preface.</note> been the Deſign of your ſmall Treatiſe, though written againſt Papiſts: adding that, <q rend="margQuotes"> Nothing can be more unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <note place="margin">ib.</note> then this, that thoſe (Churches or Church-Rulers) ſhould Lord it over the Faith or conſcientious perſwaſion of other men, who are not certain but they may err and be deceived them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</q> For that would be to take the Pope's Chair, and ſucceed into his room.</p>
               <p n="7">7. This therefore having been by your ſelf acknowledged your Deſign, I muſt repeat what I have already ſaid: That the Engliſh Biſhops and Clergy are far more intereſſed in your Book, for all the Title be only againſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, then Catholicks are. But as to this horrible poſition of Yours, which utterly deſtroys all Order and peace: Let me tell You that to particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Church-Rulers (if they be members of the Catholick Church) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility is not at all neceſſary to make their Doctrines or Orders obliging even in conſcience: Becauſe all their ſubjects whileſt they remain ſo, are bound, I do not ſay to believe internally, but not to contradict their declared Doctrines, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:205240:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> to ſubmit to their Orders: the refuſing of either perhaps not damning, but certainly excluding the refuſers from an outward communion with that Church. So that here you plainly, <hi>exerto Capite,</hi> tell the World you are no Engliſh proteſtant, though perhaps you would fain have an Engliſh Benefice, and preach againſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Engliſh pulpits.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Now as for that <hi>Great Queſtion of the Infallibility of the Church,</hi> which You conſider only as <hi>the conceit of ſome few Catholicks,</hi> if You have a mind to write any thing to the purpoſe, to prevent Your miſtaking (if that be a poſſible thing) give a well-wiſhing friend leave to informe you in general, <hi>That there is extant no formal Deciſion of the Church touching her own infallibility:</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all Catholicks are bound to acknowledge her to be infallible, by a neceſſary conſequence of an eſſential Article of the Creed. Which conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence You may conceive to be thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 9. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is an Article of our Creed <hi>Credo unam Sanctam Catholicam &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicam Eccleſiam,</hi> that is, <hi>I believe one</hi> (and but One) <hi>holy Catholick and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Church.</hi> By which Article ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:205240:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> profeſſed, the perſon, declaring himſelf a Chriſtian, ſignifies a neceſſity of his being truly a member in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with that One Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently renounces all other Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and all Eccleſiaſtical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with perſons divided from that One Church.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Second Place,</hi> Your only Guide, common ſence and reaſon tells us that a multitude cannot be called <hi>One Society,</hi> except they be joyned and link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together by a Government and Lawes common to all. And therefore the whole Catholick Church, being indeed one Body (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes) and one General Congregation, it muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily have both general Rulers, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawes univerſally obliging, which does not at all hinder but that under and within that general Congregation there may be many diſtinct Societies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying particular Lawes, Priviledges and Rulers, upon condition they do not contradict, nor refuſe to ſubmit to the ſaid general Laws, Tribunals and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</p>
               <p n="11"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 11. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> our Lord having expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſed to preſerve and continue this Church, as one Society, to the end
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:205240:47"/> of the World, ſo as that <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it:</hi> it followes undeniably, that he has provided ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and efficacious means to preſerve this unity: for otherwiſe one <hi>Article of the Creed</hi> might happen to fail.</p>
               <p n="12"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 12. <hi>In the fourth place,</hi> ſince univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Experience both in Humane and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine matters teſtifies, that never any <hi>Writing, Law,</hi> or <hi>Science</hi> could yet be ſo expreſſed, but that being left to the wits, <hi>enlightned Reaſon,</hi> and intereſts of particular men to deſcant upon them, there would follow differences of ſences and interpretations, and conſequently <hi>Diviſions</hi> and ſeparated intereſts deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to unity: to provide againſt which the only poſſible remedy hath alwaies been acknowledged to be the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an <hi>External</hi> laſting <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Magistrates.</hi> Hence it is, that the <hi>Supreme Tribunal of a General Council</hi> has evermore hitherto been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by all <hi>Christians</hi> to be the only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt a breach in the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church: and becauſe it cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be poſſible to ſummon ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, therefore by way of proviſion the <hi>ſupreme Pastour</hi> of the Church hath alwaies exerciſed, in matters that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:205240:48"/> the <hi>common Faith,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> an <hi>Authority,</hi> if not to decide, at leaſt to compoſe and ſilence all differences in Opinions, &amp;c. and to put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of precedent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Now if You will diſcourſe to any purpoſe in oppoſition to this (as I know You have a great <hi>Tooth</hi> againſt it) You muſt either demonſtrate that there is no need at all that controverſies ſhould be compoſed and Schiſmes healed: Or if You cannot do this, You muſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the Experience of all mankind, by ſhewing that <hi>Judges</hi> are not neceſſary to end <hi>Law-ſuites, that writings</hi> alone with <hi>enlightned reaſon</hi> will do the buſineſs: and eſpecially that above all Lawes and Sciences, the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> that are in ſome places infinitely obſcure, and in plain places compiled in a popular ſtile, far from that ſtudied exactneſs of Lawes and Sciences, are moſt proper to have their ſence agreed in. This muſt be your task, and to make it good, it will be expected that You ſhould do one <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle</hi> more, which is, to produce but one Example during ſixteen hundred years and upwards, taking in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, if You pleaſe, to ſhew that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:205240:48"/> 
                  <hi>differences</hi> in Religion have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented or compoſed, and ſeparations of divided Churches re-united by diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of Scriptures alone, without ſubmiſſion to a common Tribunal. On the contrary ſide we <hi>Catholicks</hi> will be obliged to ſhew you that all Hereſies hitherto appearing have been ſo far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by General Councils, that the Church has been preſerved in Unity, and we are confident will be ſo for ever, notwithſtanding even ſo formidable an Adverſaries oppoſition, as you are.</p>
               <p n="14"> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 14. In the fifth place, This great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal of a General Council is of an Authority ſo authentick, that no Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from it muſt be admitted. Yea moreover it has influence not on the outward actions or profeſſions only, but even the judgments and hearts of all particular Catholick perſons and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. This appears not only by the univerſal agreement of all Fathers and Eccleſiaſtical Writers paſt and preſent, but by the ſolemn ſtile of the Decrees made by all ſuch Councils, in which <hi>Anathema</hi>'s have been denounced againſt all Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, and they ſeparated from the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, to which alone Salvation is promiſed.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:205240:49"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 15. In the laſt place therefore, the Church being one, and to keep it ſo, Authority having been communicated to it by our Lord, which Authority for that purpoſe muſt needs under pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of an Eternal ſeparation from Chriſt oblige all Chriſtians to ſubmit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their minds to it, it ſeems to us that it followes neceſſarily and inevitably, <hi>that the Church is infallible:</hi> Unleſs we would ſay, that our Lord has comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us to hear ſuch a Church and Guide as might lead us to Hell. To prevent all ſuſpicion of which he has expreſly promiſed to lead (not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles only, as you fancy, but) <hi>his Church into all Truth, with whom</hi> he ſaid he would <hi>be preſent to the end of the world,</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of years after the Apoſtles were dead.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Theſe you may ſuppoſe, Mr. <hi>Bag.</hi> to be the true grounds of the Churches Infallibility. It is Infallible becauſe it is <hi>One,</hi> but, it is ſuch an <hi>One</hi> from which as Separation is damnable. So that if you, a Presbyterian, or Independent, &amp;c. have a minde to aſſault theſe grounds; then 1. You muſt firſt deſtroy that Article of our Creed, <hi>I believe one Catholick Church.</hi> 2. Next you muſt prove out of expreſs
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:205240:49"/> Scripture not only that Scripture is our only Rule, but that we have no other Guide to find out the ſence of it but only our private reaſon or ſpirit: and what theſe joyn'd together conclude up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will infallibly ſerve our turn, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be true or falſe. 3. That all the Antient Church and all Proteſtants too are miſtaken when they ſay that Schiſm, (to you the moſt innocent thing in the World) is a <hi>Sin,</hi> a great exterminating <hi>ſin, for which there cannot poſſibly be a juſt cauſe,</hi> or ſufficient excuſe. 4. Laſtly, you muſt have the confidence befitting a Presbyterian to ſay, that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans before you have been poor ſpirited ſheepiſh, deceived people, that knew not what the Liberty of a Subject was: and that all General Councils that preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to denounce <hi>Anathema's</hi> againſt the private ſpirit or enlightned reaſon, have been moſt abhorred conſpiracies of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants over Mens ſouls.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Whereas if you were an Engliſh Proteſtant truly ſo called, (but the very ſuppoſition is unſufferable, and therefore muſt be changed, therefore I ſay) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a true Engliſh Proteſtant would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt his readineſs to ſubmit both his tongue and ſoul to a lawful General
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:205240:50"/> Council, and conſequently would have no quarrel againſt the Infallibility of the Univerſal Church: He would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Tradition to be the beſt Interpreter of Scripture: Only his Controverſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humour would ſpend it ſelf againſt the <hi>Roman Churches</hi> pretention to the Title of Catholick, and would maintain that the Engliſh State and Clergy had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority enough to reform themſelves without conſulting the <hi>Roman,</hi> or any other <hi>Churches:</hi> Indeed if the <hi>Eaſtern Church</hi> had ſtill been in Union with the Roman the caſe then would be altered. The Engliſh Church on ſuch a ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would have had a ſcruple to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe both.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Therefore ſince it is not in our power to oblige the <hi>Turk</hi> to permit the Eaſtern Biſhops to meet in a General Council with the Weſt: for Engliſh Proteſtants ſake (not yours, good Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw)</hi> I will take upon me a little more then your Book can require from me, and that is to propoſe in the mean time a convenient mean and expedient towards the removing this ſcruple: and that is as followeth.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Since we cannot have ſpeaking Judges that will pleaſe them, they may,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:205240:50"/> I ſuppoſe, do well to help themſelves with Books: and for that purpoſe pitch upon ſome well known time in which the <hi>Eastern</hi> and <hi>Western Churches</hi> were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and out of the <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> of that <hi>Age</hi> impartially collect the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines then taught, and the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government then in uſe through the whole Church: For thereby it will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear whether of the <hi>Churches, Eaſtern</hi> or <hi>Weſtern</hi> that now differ in both, have deſerted that which was anciently in both.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Now I conceive a more proper time for this purpoſe cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then the <hi>Age</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great's time when <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was converted from <hi>Paganiſme</hi> by St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the Monk ſent by him. For it is evident that the whole Church was then in perfect Union: the ſame Doctrines were taught, and the ſame Government and Common laws in uſe all the Chriſtian World over. Beſides, there are extant more, better and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Monuments both of the Doctrines and Diſcipline of that Age then in any other: and eſpecially in St. <hi>Gregories</hi> Epiſtles ſent into all quarters of the World, and in other of his works tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:205240:51"/> into the Greek tongue, and freely embraced, yea admired by the Greek Church, we may find what Authority ſo learned and Holy a Pope exerciſed over other Churches according to the then received Eccleſiaſtical Canons. Moreover beſides S. <hi>Gregories</hi> Works, our own Country both by wtitings of learned men, Councils of Biſhops, and viſible Marks in the foundation of Churches and Monaſteries, will moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly furniſh us.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Now when we have found what in that age was the Belief and practiſe of the whole Church uniformly: Then we are to confront thereto the Doctrines and Diſcipline of the preſent <hi>Eastern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern Churches:</hi> Being aſſured that both of them have not deſerted the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Belief and practiſe: becauſe if it were ſo, there would not now be extant any <hi>Orthodox Church</hi> at all: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our <hi>Saviours promiſe</hi> of <hi>leading his Church into all Truth</hi> would have failed.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Now when it ſhall appear unto us whether of theſe two great Churches hath preſerved the <hi>Antient faith</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> we ſhall neceſſarily be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to a Communion with that Church:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:205240:51"/> becauſe a ſeparation from it will be a manifeſt Apoſtacy and Schiſm from the moſt certainly <hi>one, true, Catholick Church,</hi> and conſequently from <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Now that the preſent Roman Church does at this day profeſs the very ſame Doctrines, and is govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame Laws, that were in force in St. <hi>Gregories</hi> dayes, will as ſeems to us evidently appear both from his Writings, the Eceleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſince, and the Antient Engliſh Councils: as likewiſe by the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of ſeveral learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. To this purpoſe Doctor <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phreys</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Humphr. Jeſuitis <hi>in par.</hi> 2. <hi>rat.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 627.</note> writes thus, <hi>In Eccleſiam verò quid invexerunt</hi> Gregorius <hi>&amp;</hi> Auguſtinus? <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ceraemoniarum,</hi> &amp;c. that is. <q rend="margQuotes"> But now what have <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Austin</hi> brought into the Church? A burden of Ceremonies, &amp;c. the Archiepiſcopal Pall to be uſed at Solemn Maſs, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, &amp;c. the Oblation of the Holy Hoſt and prayers for the Dead, &amp;c. Relicks, &amp;c. Tranſubſtantiation, &amp;c. new Conſecrations of Churches, &amp;c.</q> To theſe particulars <hi>Carion</hi> a <hi>Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Carion. Chron. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 567.</note> adds <q rend="margQuotes"> the publick Rite of Invocation of Saints, a falſe perſwaſion concerning a Monaſtical profeſſion, works deviſed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:205240:52"/> without any precept of God, ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vowes, &amp;c. And whereas (ſaith he) <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf did tragically declaim, and profeſs his abhorring the Title of Univerſal Biſhop, yet in reality he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that himſelf did vehemently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the thing ſignified by that Title, ſince he took upon him a commanding power over other Churches.</q> To theſe may be added the Centuriators of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburg, Bale,</hi> &amp;c. who mention theſe and other particular Doctrines, as No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties introduced by <hi>St. Gregory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. Hence if our Adverſaries ſpeak truth it will evidently follow, that ſince there are now differences between the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern Churches,</hi> all the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations and innovations have been made by the <hi>Greek Church</hi> only.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Do you not now ſee, Mr, <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> what Religion that is, the profeſſours whereof you, as far as your vote extends, expoſe to the Butchery? whence is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that if you had been a leader of a party able to execute your cruel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in S. <hi>Gregories</hi> dayes, you would like a very <hi>Antichrist,</hi> have laid waſt the whole <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> and murdred all that were called by his name. There wants only this to crown your zeal, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:205240:52"/> you ſhould cry out, <hi>Their blood be upon us and upon our children.</hi> Thus would you have treated S. <hi>Augustin</hi> and his fellow <hi>Monks,</hi> you I ſay, that the leſs Charity you have, eſteem your ſelves the more perfect Chriſtians and Saints, you would have condemn'd to <hi>Gallowſes, quartering of members,</hi> and <hi>burning of bowels</hi> thoſe innocent perſons that expoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to all incommodities for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Country: when as our <hi>Pagan Ancestors,</hi> though Slaves of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, yet treated them with all humanity. Take heed they do not <hi>riſe in judgment against you:</hi> I am ſure in that great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you ſhall not riſe to condemn them for this ſin.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">1. THus <hi>Sir,</hi> I have performed as much as I promiſed in the beginning: and truly I promiſed more then your Book deſerved: In which I found ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall a proportion of Reaſon em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, that I may perhaps incur cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for miſpending time about a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that would not indanger the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leading of any. I muſt therefore plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell the Reader that it was only your <hi>paſſion,</hi> Your cruelly malicious ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:205240:53"/> that I intended to oppoſe: That is your proper <hi>Engin</hi> to do miſchief with, to prevent which, a Chriſtian compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to thouſands of innocent, peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſouls whoſe deſtruction your paſſion deſignes, does require all honeſt mens endeavours and care. You acknowledge <hi>enlightned reaſon</hi> for your only Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: but I find that which You call by ſuch a name to be nothing elſe but a reſtleſs fancy, ſwelling with ſelf opinion, and inflamed with almoſt all ſorts of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate paſſions, ſharpned againſt all moderate perſons, both Proteſtants and Catholicks, that is, againſt all that have any ſence of Duty to the King, or love of peace among Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Now as among <hi>Protestants</hi> You thought fit to ſingle out only two, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>Gunning</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi> through whoſe ſides You would wound all that are not as furious againſt peace as your ſelf: So among Catholicks likewiſe there are two, my Lord the Earle of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Earle of</hi> Briſtow. <hi>Fiat Lux</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Briſtow,</hi> and the Authour of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> againſt whom you have thruſt forth a forked ſting armed with poyſon enough, but wanting ſtrength to make that poyſon enter. I hope his Lordſhip will pardon a ſtranger, yet an admirer of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:205240:53"/> his moſt eminent abilities and vertues, for taking notice without order from him, of your malicious reflexions upon him, which might be prejudicial to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, were it not that it comes from a perſon that I am aſſured he will never dignify with anſwering.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. You reckon his Lordſhip in the Catalogue of thoſe who have ſhewed the <q rend="margQuotes"> vanity and uſeleſsneſs of Allegations <note place="margin">Preface.</note> of Authorities, of Fathers, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, &amp;c. And becauſe <hi>(ſay you)</hi> it is poſſible that the example of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Perſon may be urged againſt me, ſince his preſent practiſe doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his former principles, I will only add this, that ſince his book is not yet anſwered by himſelf, I hope he thinks it unanſwerable, and will not long continue in communion with that Church, whoſe foundations he hath ſo well overthrown.</q> An Admirable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage this is, fit for no pen but Mr. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaws.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That his Lordſhip has not yet pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd an Anſwer to a Writing of his own, ſufficiently confuted by his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, I ſhould rather think you might have imputed to ſuch as your ſelf. Theſe are not times for any of his Lordſhips
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:205240:54"/> preſent perſwaſion in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to multiply unneceſſary controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of that Nature. And however, your ſelf and your party afford ſuch as his Lordſhip is buſineſs enough to exerciſe all their abilities prudence and skill, in oppoſing your ſecret workings and open calumnies, by demonſtrating that a change in his perſwaſion about points of faith doth make no change at all in his Fidelity. And thus much his Lordſhip (in the name of all Catholicks) to your great grief has performed with that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, candour and energy, that I am confident there is not a Proteſtant that ſhall read your infamous aſperſions caſt upon <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> touching the matter of Loyalty, but will look upon them as the laſt effects of the deſperate rage of one that takes pleaſure in mere calumniating, without any expectation to be believ'd.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And truly, <hi>Sir,</hi> if you had taken to task the making the World believe that in your Sect Chriſtian Charity is eſteemed a mortal ſin, you could not have better effected your deſign then by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as you have done, <hi>I hope his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thinks his Book unanſwerable,</hi> &amp;c. For ſhame change this phraſe, <hi>I hope,</hi> &amp;c. It
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:205240:54"/> would have been an impudence not to be pardon'd had you only ſaid <hi>I fear,</hi> or <hi>I ſuſpect</hi> this: But ſure there is not any Chriſtian, except Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> whoſe Religion would allow him to ſay, <q rend="margQuotes"> I hope his Lordſhip thinks his Book un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable: that is in effect, I hope in God that his Lordſhip is both an Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical Hypocrite, profeſſing a Religion contrary to his conſcience, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that his Hypocriſie, againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that ſin, is ſenceleſly void of all worldly pretentions, ſince he counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits a Religion that he knowes is rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous to his fortunes.</q> Is this your <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological vertue</hi> of <hi>Hope?</hi> Truly it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you well: Your <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> I ſee are all of a piece.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It may be you knew ſome Great Men that for ſome ends you could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to ſtrain their conſciences ſo far as to profeſs a Religion that themſelves are able to confute. But ſure they will be no loſers by it: whatever becomes of ther ſouls, care ſhall be taken that their worldly Eſtate ſhall thrive by it: They will declare for a Sect where money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds, and where power and Offices may be ſhared: That is, of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>England</hi> they will take heed of the <hi>Catholick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:205240:55"/> 7. Indeed if you underſtood what <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion</hi> is, you would never ſay ſo much, as <hi>I ſuſpect,</hi> &amp;c. and if you knew what <hi>Christian Religion</hi> is you would never have ſaid <hi>I hope</hi> ſuch an abominable, ſo unreaſonable a thing. In your Sect I conceive ſuch an <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie</hi> may be practiſed at a cheaper rate. But in Catholick Religion no Man can commit that ſin alone: it muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be attended with moſt horrible ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge and a ſolemn profanation of two <hi>Sacraments, Pennance</hi> and the <hi>Holy Euchariſt.</hi> Therefore I hope that you have been bold to bely your ſelf when you ſaid, <hi>I hope his Lordſhip thinks his Book unanſwerable.</hi> I have a better opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of you, then you deſire I ſhould.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. As for the Author of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained <note place="margin">Fiat Lux Epiſt. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> of by you to your Honourable Patron in the Epiſtle Dedicatory, where you lay to his charge <hi>Blaſphemies that you</hi> (good man) tremble to mention: If you had ſincerely related thoſe paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and were they conſidered not as ſtanding alone, but with the dependance on what is delivered before, they will be ſo far from deſerving to be called Blaſphemies, that no ſober charitable Reader will deny them to be ſimple
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:205240:55"/> unſtrain'd Truths. And if you think good to reply to theſe papers I here undertake to juſtifie thoſe paſſages in the proper true ſence that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor apparently meant them. Which that it is no hard matter to do I will ſhew you preſently: His firſt paſſage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by you is this: <hi>In my judgment</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Chriſt our Lord hath no leſs ſhewn his Divinity and power in the Pope, then in himſelf. And all things conſidered, I may truly ſay, that Chriſt in the Pope and Church is more miraculous, then in his own perſon.</hi> My reaſon to demonſtrate the truth of this (which is the Authors too (is this, becauſe the preſervation of the Church in Unity and Truth under the Government of ſupream Paſtours, without interruption for ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years and more amongſt ſo many tryals and oppoſitions, is a greater effect of a Divine power in Chriſt, then he ſhew'd in prolonging his own perſonal life for about thirty three years.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. And as to the ſecond paſſage, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That the firſt great Fundamental of Chriſtian Religion, which is the truth and Divinity of Chriſt, had it not been for the Pope, had failed long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go in the World. So that I may truly
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:205240:56"/> ſay, that Chriſt is the Popes God: For if the Pope had not been, or had not been ſo vigilant a Paſtor as he is, Chriſt had not been taken now for any ſuch perſon as he is believed this day.</q> Conſult your books, and the whole <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Eccleſiaſtical Story</hi> will inform you that the <hi>Pope</hi> by means of <hi>Councels</hi> of the <hi>Weſtern Church</hi> aſſembled by his Authority was he alone that inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally deſtroy'd <hi>Arianiſme</hi> and other <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies</hi> denying the <hi>Divinity of Christ,</hi> which for ſome ages had in a manner poyſon'd all the <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. And laſtly without much boaſting I may with him conclude. <q rend="margQuotes"> This I may boldly ſay, and am aſſured of, that if the Pope be not an unerring Guide in affairs of Religion, that way I mean that I have ſhewn him in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to have exerciſed his Guidance [by General Councils,] all is loſt.</q> For this is no other then what with all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks I have aſſerted and will poſitively juſtifie, <q rend="margQuotes"> that the authority of the Church in her ſupream Tribunals is the only aſſured means of preſerving the Church in Unity, as being an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from which no Appeals muſt be admitted, that is, being Infallible.</q>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:205240:56"/> Theſe therefore, you ſee, are no ſuch Blaſphemies as to put you into a fit of trembling.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. I do now expect, <hi>Sir,</hi> unleſs God inſpire more charity into your heart, that you will make loud complaints of the preſumption of your Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick adverſary, for daring to defend his Religion againſt your evident miſtakes, and the cauſe of all his profeſſion from the trayterous imputation of a <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on a forreign authority,</hi> moſt unjuſtly by you laid to their charge: like the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gladiatour, you will accuſe us for avoyding your blows and thruſts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not <hi>recipere totum gladium.</hi> But this Confidence is the effect of our Innocence only, which as the Scripture ſays, <hi>Gives the boldneſſe of a lyon.</hi> Nay, it is for your ſake, if you pleaſe; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is for our Countreys ſake, that we beg no more innocent blood may be laid to its charge. But if it muſt ſtill be ſpilt, we had rather you ſhould be our Executioners, than any other. We give Almighty God, and the Parliament moſt humble thanks, that we have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to wipe off the ſcandal of Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity from our Religion: This we tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in. Hereafter if we ſuffer, we call
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:205240:57"/> God to witneſs, and the whole Kingdom (I mean Engliſh Proteſtants) that it will be purely our Conſcience, our Religion, our love of Peace and Unity that we ſuffer for; for all manner of ſecurity we have, and ever will give of being faithfull, quiet, good Subjects: all Oaths expreſſing only our obligation to Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or acknowledgment of the Kings temporal Supreamacy we will take. Does it not become then ſuch Sufferers to be confident? Does it not become ſuch lovers of their Countrey to wiſh that no more guilt may lye upon it? True it is, we look upon your party as our Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, you give us up into their hands, you kill us with their ſwords. They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to mercy, being ſatisfyed of our Innocency: but you threaten to ſet the Kingdom on fire, with your crying out <hi>Popery,</hi> if they ſpare us. We do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from his Majeſty, that for our ſakes (though his moſt loyal Subjects) he ſhould take upon himſelf the envy that you would raiſe againſt him. We beſeech him he would not: indeed he ought not to do it, conſidering the miſchief that may follow, is publick, and threatning the whole Kingdom. But the generality of Proteſtants, me thinks, have little
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:205240:57"/> reaſon to fear your clamours, when they extend mercy to innocent perſons. And therefore thoſe that by their Offices have an influence upon our Lawes, and are able to abate the ſharpneſs of them, yea have thought fit to take it into conſideration, if they, either out of complyance, or fear of You, forbear to do what Civil Juſtice, and much more, Chriſtian Charity, requires, they muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that God will hold them innocent: It will be a great mercy if he puniſheth them in this world, either in their eſtates perſons or families.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. You know the Goſpel Story: I would to God You would make better uſe of it: The Jewiſh Prieſts and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees accuſed our Saviour of ſeditious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: and for that delivered him into the hands of the Romans. What did they lay to his charge? <hi>Art thou a King?</hi> ſaid <hi>Pilate,</hi> that was his charge: He aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes (ſaid they) a power contrary to <hi>Caeſars.</hi> Our Saviour acknowledges that he was a King: that he challenged a Supremacy of power: and that he came to conſtitute a new Kingdom upon earth: but it was a Kingdom not of this world: it was a power purely ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, ſo far from being prejudicial to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:205240:58"/> 
                     <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that one of the fundamentall Lawes of this ſpiritual Kingdom was, <hi>That whatſoever belonged to Caeſar ſhould be given to him:</hi> not one dram of Civil authority ſhould be taken from him. The Romans were ſatisfied with his anſwer: <hi>Pilate</hi> proteſted him innocent. But all little purpoſe, for the Phariſees make clamours, they ſtir the people to ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they threaten <hi>Pilate:</hi> and the Text ſayes, the clamours of the Phariſees and people ſo wholly prevailed, that our Saviour was <hi>delivered up unto their will, to do unto him even what they pleaſed.</hi> All that <hi>Pilate</hi> durſt to do was to <hi>waſh his hands,</hi> and proclaim the violence uſed upon him: but however he judged him to death, and the Romans crucified him. Now not any man will acquit <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> though a greater damnation be due to the Phariſees. <hi>Pilates</hi> crime was heynous, but it was humane, he would fain have done juſtice, but he feared a ſedition, he had not the courage to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Juſtice. But the Phariſees crime was Diabolical, and as they behaved themſelves by crying out, <hi>His blood be on us and our Children,</hi> it became unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: both the temporal and eternal deſtruction of the whole nation was the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:205240:58"/> reward of it. But now conſider who theſe Prieſts and Phariſees were that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed our Saviour of ſeditious Doctrine againſt <hi>Caeſar.</hi> They were the only E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had in the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Joſephus</hi> will tell us that the principles of their Sect were treaſon and Rebellion: They only of all the Jews refuſed an Oath of Allegiance. If our Saviour would have incited his followers to caſt off <hi>Caeſars</hi> yoke, they would have joyned with him, and have made him either their King or Protectour. They had attempted ſeveral inſurrections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and within a few years after put the whole State into an open bloody Rebellion, which ended in their utter deſtruction. Yet ſuch power had theſe mens malicious ſuggeſtions as to make our Saviour be condemned as a Traytour: His Diſciples therefore muſt not think to be bettter uſed then their Maſter, I mean by Phariſees.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> here is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſaid to your Stating of that <hi>great Queſtion of Infallibility,</hi> as you have ſtated it: And more then You will think enough, to Your cruelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Roman Catholicks. If you have any ſuſpition that we have not expreſſed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:205240:59"/> our mindes clearly and ſatisfactorily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; Upon any exceptions You will pleaſe to make, more ſhall be ſaid. And as touching what hath been here delivered about diſowning a forreign power prejudicial to the State, do not read it as the aſſertion of one ſingle Roman Catholick: But be aſſured that if ever theſe papers be offered to Your eyes to be read, You will read that which has been approved, and will be juſtifyed by many Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons of the ſame Religion, perſons of Learning, Vertue and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who therefore can know, and will be anſwerable for the conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble judgments of far greater numbers that depend on their Direction reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. My deſire now is, that you would write no more againſt any Catholick Truth, or Chriſtian peace. But if You cannot for Your life hold, then I would, as a friend, adviſe you to get before hand a right notion and underſtanding of the ſubject you would write upon: and however, that You would forbear laying falſe crimes to the charge of Your brethren: The condition of Roman Catholicks is ſad
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:205240:59"/> enough: And truly it is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome for thoſe that are in a State of Uniformity with them, to add to their ſufferings. To conclude, if you think me worthy to be your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in a Pen-quarrell, let us not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about things in which You have no skill, or that will not be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but rather wound bleſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity. And if you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to propoſe a ſubject in which you and your party are believed to have much intereſt, and which if well debated, would bring much good to thouſands of ſouls in theſe Kingdomes, my deſire is it may be this Problem or Queſtion (which I told you has been taken into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>France, viz.) Whether Christian Subjects may by their Religion be allowed to defend by Armes against their Soveraign and lawful Authority their Opinions and Doctrines, in caſe theſe be perſecuted by them. For my own part I make choice of the Negative.</hi> And now I reſigne you to the mercy of Mr. <hi>L'Estrange.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:205240:60"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205240:60"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
